  <page>
    <title>Mobile phone</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>477272</id>
    <redirect title="Mobile phone" />
    <revision>
      <id>5410785</id>
      <timestamp>2013-03-20T08:11:00Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Wizzard</username>
        <id>412</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment></comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">
	  {{Redirect|Cell Phone|the film|Cell Phone (film)}}
{{Redirect|Handphone|the film|Handphone (film)}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=September 2013}}
{{pp-semi-protected|small=yes}}
[[File:Two Cell Phones 2.png|thumb|A [[Qualcomm]] QCP-2700 (left) c. 1998, and an [[iPhone 5]] (right) from 2012]]
A '''mobile phone''' (also known as a '''cellular phone''', '''cell phone''', '''hand phone''', or simply a '''phone''') is a [[telephone|phone]] that can make and receive [[telephone call]]s over a [[Radio Link Protocol|radio link]] while moving around a wide geographic area.  It does so by connecting to a [[cellular network]] provided by a [[mobile phone operator]], allowing access to the [[PSTN|public telephone network]].  By contrast, a [[cordless telephone]] is used only within the short range of a single, private base station.

In addition to telephony, modern mobile phones also support a wide variety of other [[GSM services|services]] such as [[text messaging]], [[Multimedia Messaging Service|MMS]], [[email]], Internet access, short-range wireless communications ([[infrared port|infrared]], [[Bluetooth]]), business applications, gaming, and photography. Mobile phones that offer these and more general computing capabilities are referred to as [[smartphone]]s.

The first hand-held cell phone was demonstrated by [[John Francis Mitchell|John F. Mitchell]]<ref>[http://www.brophy.net/PivotX/?p=john-francis-mitchell-biography John F. Mitchell Biography]</ref><ref>[http://www.brophy.net/PivotX/?p=john-francis-mitchell-biography#CELLPHONEINVENTOR Who invented the cell phone?]</ref> and [[Martin Cooper (inventor)|Dr. Martin Cooper]] of [[Motorola]] in 1973, using a handset weighing around 4.4 pounds (2&nbsp;kg).<ref name="Inventor">{{cite journal | last = Heeks | first = Richard | year = 2008 | title = Meet Marty Cooper – the inventor of the mobile phone | journal = BBC | volume = 41 | issue = 6 | url = http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/programmes/click_online/8639590.stm | pages = 26–33 | doi = 10.1109/MC.2008.192 }}</ref>
In 1983, the [[Motorola DynaTAC|DynaTAC 8000x]] was the first to be commercially available. From 1990 to 2011, worldwide mobile phone subscriptions grew from 12.4 million to over 6 billion, penetrating about 87% of the global population and reaching the [[bottom of the pyramid|bottom of the economic pyramid]].<ref name="gartner">{{cite news|url=http://www.itu.int/net/pressoffice/press_releases/2012/70.aspx
|title=ITU releases latest global technology development figures | work=ITU|date=9 July 2010}}</ref><ref name="Heeks">{{cite news|url=http://mobithinking.com/mobile-marketing-tools/latest-mobile-stats/a#subscribers
|title=Global mobile statistics 2012 Part A: Mobile subscribers; handset market share; mobile operators|work=Mobithinking|date=9 August 2012}}</ref><ref>{{cite web|url=http://www.worldmapper.org/display.php?selected=333 |title=The world as you've never seen it before |publisher=Worldmapper |accessdate=26 August 2010}}</ref><ref>{{cite book |title=The Mobile Wave: How Mobile Intelligence Will Change Everything |last=Saylor |first=Michael |year=2012 |publisher=Perseus Books/Vanguard Press |isbn=978-1593157203 |page=5 }}</ref> In 2013, the top cell phone manufacturers were [[Samsung Electronics|Samsung]], [[Nokia]], [[Apple Inc.]], and [[LG Electronics|LG]].

== History ==
{{Main|History of mobile phones}}
[[File:Mobile phone evolution.jpg|thumb|An evolution of mobile phones]]

A hand-held mobile radiotelephone is an old dream of radio engineering. One of the earliest descriptions can be found in the 1948 science fiction novel [[Space Cadet]] by [[Robert Heinlein]]. The protagonist, who has just traveled to Colorado from his home in Iowa, receives a call from his father on a telephone in his pocket. Before leaving for earth orbit, he decides to ship the telephone home "since it was limited by its short range to the neighborhood of an earth-side [i.e. terrestrial] relay office." Ten years later, an essay by [[Arthur C. Clarke]] envisioned a "personal transceiver, so small and compact that every man carries one." Clarke wrote: "the time will come when we will be able to call a person anywhere on Earth merely by dialing a number." Such a device would also, in Clarke's vision, include means for global positioning so that "no one need ever again be lost." Later, in ''Profiles of the Future'', he predicted the advent of such a device taking place in the mid-1980s.<ref name="profiles">Arthur C. Clarke: ''Profiles of the Future'' (1962, rev. eds. 1973, 1983, and 1999, Millennium edition with a new preface)</ref>

Early predecessors of cellular phones included analog radio communications from ships and trains. The race to create truly portable telephone devices began after World War II, with developments taking place in many countries. The advances in mobile telephony have been traced in successive ''generations'' from the early "0G" (zeroth generation) services like the [[Bell System]]'s [[Mobile Telephone Service]] and its successor, [[Improved Mobile Telephone Service]]. These "0G" systems were not cellular, supported few simultaneous calls, and were very expensive.

The first handheld mobile cell phone was demonstrated by [[Motorola]] in 1973. The first commercial automated cellular network was launched in Japan by [[Nippon Telegraph and Telephone|NTT]] in 1979. In 1981, this was followed by the simultaneous launch of the [[Nordic Mobile Telephone]] (NMT) system in Denmark, Finland, Norway and Sweden.<ref>{{cite web|url=http://www.tekniskamuseet.se/mobilen/engelska/1980_90.shtml |title=Swedish National Museum of Science and Technology |publisher=Tekniskamuseet.se |accessdate=29 July 2009}}</ref>  Several other countries then followed in the early to mid-1980s. These first generatiion ("1G") systems could support far more simultaneous calls, but still used analog technology.

In 1991, the second generation ([[2G]]) ''digital'' cellular technology was launched in Finland by [[Radiolinja]] on the [[GSM]] standard, which sparked competition in the sector, as the new operators challenged the incumbent 1G network operators.

Ten years later, in 2001, the third generation ([[3G]]) was launched in Japan by [[NTT DoCoMo]] on the [[WCDMA]] standard.<ref>{{cite web|author=UMTS World |url=http://www.umtsworld.com/umts/history.htm |title=History of UMTS and 3G development |publisher=Umtsworld.com |accessdate=29 July 2009}}</ref> This was followed by 3.5G, 3G+ or turbo 3G enhancements based on the [[High-Speed Packet Access|high-speed packet access]] (HSPA) family, allowing [[Universal Mobile Telecommunications System|UMTS networks]] to have higher data transfer speeds and capacity.

By 2009, it had become clear that, at some point, 3G networks would be overwhelmed by the growth of bandwidth-intensive applications like streaming media.<ref>{{cite web | url=http://www.ece.iupui.edu/~dskim/Classes/ECE695MWN/2006-saeed-Capacity_Limit_Problem_in_3G_Networks.ppt | title=Capacity Limit Problem in 3G Networks | author=Fahd Ahmad Saeed | publisher=Purdue School of Engineering | accessdate=23 April 2010}}</ref> Consequently, the industry began looking to data-optimized 4th-generation technologies, with the promise of speed improvements up to 10-fold over existing 3G technologies. The first two commercially available technologies billed as [[4G]] were the [[WiMAX]] standard (offered in the U.S. by [[Sprint Nextel|Sprint]]) and the [[LTE (telecommunication)|LTE]] standard, first offered in Scandinavia by [[TeliaSonera]].

==Features==
{{Main|Mobile phone features}}
{{see also|Smartphone}}
[[File:Mobil uvnitr.png|thumb|A [[printed circuit board]] inside a [[Nokia 3210]] ]]
All mobile phones have a number of features in common, but manufacturers also try to differentiate their own products by implementing additional functions to make them more attractive to consumers. This has led to great innovation in mobile phone development over the past 20 years.

The common components found on all phones are:
* A [[battery (electricity)|battery]], providing the power source for the phone functions.
* An input mechanism to allow the user to interact with the phone. The most common input mechanism is a [[keypad]], but [[touch screen]]s are also found in most smartphones.
* A screen which echoes the user's typing, displays text messages, contacts and more.
* Basic [[GSM services|mobile phone services]] to allow users to make calls and send text messages.
* All [[GSM]] phones use a [[Subscriber Identity Module|SIM card]] to allow an account to be swapped among devices. Some [[CDMA]] devices also have a similar card called a [[Removable User Identity Module|R-UIM]].
* Individual GSM, WCDMA, iDEN and some [[satellite phone]] devices are uniquely identified by an [[International Mobile Equipment Identity]] ([[International Mobile Equipment Identity|IMEI]]) number.

Low-end mobile phones are often referred to as [[feature phone]]s, and offer basic telephony.  Handsets with more advanced computing ability through the use of native software applications became known as [[smartphone]]s.

Several phone series have been introduced to address a given market segment, such as the RIM [[BlackBerry]] focusing on enterprise/corporate customer email needs; the Sony-Ericsson 'Walkman' series of music/phones and 'Cybershot' series of camera/phones; the [[Nokia Nseries]] of multimedia phones, the [[Palm Pre]] the [[HTC Dream]] and the Apple [[iPhone]].

===Text messaging===
{{main|SMS}}
The most commonly used data application on mobile phones is [[SMS]] text messaging. The first SMS text message was sent from a computer to a mobile phone in 1992 in the UK, while the first person-to-person SMS from phone to phone was sent in Finland in 1993.

The first [[mobile news]] service, delivered via SMS, was launched in Finland in 2000, and subsequently many organizations provided "on-demand" and "instant" news services by SMS.

===SIM card===
{{Main|Subscriber Identity Module|Removable User Identity Module}}
[[File:Typical cellphone SIM cards.jpg|thumb|Typical mobile phone [[SIM card]]]]

[[GSM]] [[feature phone]]s require a small [[Integrated circuit|microchip]] called a Subscriber Identity Module or [[SIM card]], to function. The SIM card is approximately the size of a small postage stamp and is usually placed underneath the battery in the rear of the unit. The SIM securely stores the [[International Mobile Subscriber Identity|service-subscriber key (IMSI)]] and the [[Authentication Center#Authentication centre (AuC)|K<sub>i</sub>]] used to identify and authenticate the user of the mobile phone. The SIM card allows users to change phones by simply removing the SIM card from one mobile phone and inserting it into another mobile phone or broadband telephony device, provided that this is not prevented by a [[SIM lock]].

The first SIM card was made in 1991 by Munich smart card maker [[Giesecke & Devrient]] for the Finnish wireless network operator [[Radiolinja]]. {{Citation needed|date=May 2013}}

===Multi-card hybrid phones===
A hybrid mobile phone can hold up to four SIM cards. SIM and RUIM cards may be mixed together to allow both [[GSM]] and [[CDMA]] networks to be accessed.<ref>[http://www.trisimphones.com/category/ht-g78 Example of a Triple SIM hybrid phone]</ref><ref>[http://www.trisimphones.com/quad-sim-phones/the-latest-f160-quad-sim-quad-standby-tv-java-phone-with-qwerty-keyboard The Latest F160 Quad Sim Quad Standby TV Java Phone with Qwerty Keyboard | Tri Sim Phones<!-- Bot generated title -->]</ref>

From 2010 onwards they became popular in India and Indonesia and other emerging markets,<ref>[http://news.yahoo.com/s/nm/20110429/wr_nm/us_handsets] {{dead link|date=September 2011}}</ref> attributed to the desire to obtain the lowest on-net calling rate.  In Q3 2011, [[Nokia]] shipped 18 million of its low cost dual SIM phone range in an attempt to make up lost ground in the higher end smartphone market.<ref>{{cite web |url=http://www.ft.com/intl/cms/s/0/11bbf530-fb11-11e0-bebe-00144feab49a.html#axzz1bTfJxgTz |title=Nokia boosted by sales of cheap handsets |date=20 October 2011}}</ref>

===Kosher phones===
There are [[Jewish orthodox]] religious restrictions which, by some interpretations, standard mobile telephones do not meet. To solve this issue, some rabbinical organizations have recommended that phones with text messaging capability not be used by children.<ref>[http://www.theworld.org/2012/01/kosher-phones-orthodox-jews/ Pri's The World: Kosher Phones For Britain’s Orthodox Jews]</ref> These [[Telephone numbers in Israel#"Kosher" numbers|restricted phones]] are known as [[kosher]] phones and have [[rabbi]]nical approval for use in Israel and elsewhere by observant [[Orthodox Jew]]s. Although these phones are intended to prevent [[Immodesty#Jewish modesty|immodesty]], some vendors report good sales to adults who prefer the simplicity of the devices. Some phones are even approved for use by essential workers (such as health, security and public services) on the [[Shabbat|sabbath]], even though use of any electrical device is generally prohibited.<ref name=kosher>[http://www.israelnationalnews.com/News/News.aspx/154153 israelnationalnews.com: Introducing: A 'Kosher Phone' Permitted on Shabbat]</ref>

==Mobile phone operators==
[[File:Mobile phone map 1980-2009.gif|thumb|Global mobile phone subscribers per country from 1980 to 2009. The growth in users has been exponential since they were first made available.]]
{{main|Mobile phone operator}}
The world's largest individual mobile operator by subscribers is [[China Mobile]] with over 500 million mobile phone subscribers.<ref>{{cite web|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/business/2010/jan/11/china-mobile-telecomms|title=State owned China Mobile is world's biggest mobile phone operator|author=Tania Branigan|date=11 January 2010|publisher=Guardian News and Media Limited|accessdate=17 December 2011}}</ref> Over 50 mobile operators have over 10 million subscribers each, and over 150 mobile operators had at least one million subscribers by the end of 2009.<ref>Source: wireless intelligence</ref> In February 2010, there were six billion mobile phone subscribers, a number that is expected to grow.<ref name="gartner" />

==Manufacturers==
{{See also|List of best-selling mobile phones|List of mobile phone makers by country}}
{{bar box
|width=300px
|title=Quantity Market Shares by [[Gartner]]<br>(New Sales)
|titlebar=#dddddddddddddd
|left1='''BRAND'''
|right1='''Percent'''
|float=right
|bars=
{{bar percent|Samsung 2012|Green|22.0}}
{{bar percent|Samsung 2013|Green|24.6}}
{{bar percent|Nokia 2012|Black|19.1}}
{{bar percent|Nokia 2013|Black|13.9}}
{{bar percent|Apple 2012|Red|7.5}}
{{bar percent|Apple 2013|Red|8.3}}
{{bar percent|LG Electronics 2012|Orange|3.3}}
{{bar percent|LG Electronics 2013|Orange|3.8}}
{{bar percent|ZTE 2012|Yellow|3.9}}
{{bar percent|ZTE 2013|Yellow|3.3}}
{{bar percent|Others 2012|Blue|34.9}}
{{bar percent|Others 2013|Blue|34.0}}
|caption=<small>Note: Others-1 consist of Sony Ericsson, Motorola, ZTE, HTC and Huawei.(2009-2010)</small>
}}
Prior to 2010, [[Nokia]] was the market leader. However, since then competition emerged in the Asia Pacific region with brands such as Micromax, [[Nexian]], and i-Mobile and chipped away at Nokia's market share. Android powered smartphones also gained momentum across the region at the expense of Nokia. In India, their market share also dropped significantly to around 31 percent from 56 percent in the same period. Their share was displaced by Chinese and Indian vendors of low-end mobile phones.<ref>[http://news.yahoo.com/s/pcworld/20101229/tc_pcworld/nokia8217smarketsharedropsfurtherinindia]{{Dead link|date=August 2011}}</ref>

In Q1 2012, based on Strategy Analytics, Samsung surpassed Nokia, selling 93.5 million units and 82.7 million units, respectively. [[Standard & Poor's]] has also downgraded Nokia to 'junk' status at BB+/B with negative outlook due to high loss and still declined with growth of Lumia smartphones was not sufficient to offset a rapid decline in revenue from Symbian-based smartphones over the next few quarters.<ref>{{cite web |url=http://techcrunch.com/2012/04/27/samsung-may-have-just-become-the-king-of-mobile-handsets-while-sp-downgrades-nokia-to-junk/ |title=Samsung May Have Just Become The King Of Mobile Handsets, While S&P Downgrades Nokia To Junk |accessdate=28 April 2012}}</ref>

{| class="wikitable" style="width:50%;"
|-
!colspan=4| Top Five Worldwide Total Mobile Phone Vendors, 2013
|-
!|Rank
!|Manufacturer
!|[[Gartner]]<ref>{{cite web |url= http://www.gartner.com/newsroom/id/2665715 |title=Annual Smartphone Sales Surpassed Sales of Feature Phones for the First Time in 2013|accessdate=13 February 2014}}</ref>
!|[[International Data Corporation|IDC]]<ref>{{cite web |url=http://www.idc.com/getdoc.jsp?containerId=prUS24645514 |title=Worldwide Smartphone Shipments Top One Billion Units for the First Time |accessdate=27 January 2014}}</ref>
|-
|| 1 || [[Samsung Electronics|Samsung]] || 24.6% || 24.5%
|-
|| 2 || [[Nokia]]|| 13.9% || 13.8%
|-
||3 || [[Apple Inc.]] || 8.3% || 8.4%
|-
|| 4 ||  [[LG Electronics|LG]] || 3.8% || 3.8%
|-
|| 5 || [[ZTE]] || 3.3% || -
|-
|| 5 || [[Huawei]] || - || 3.0% 
|-
|| || Others || 34.0% || 46.4%
|}
<small>
* Note: Vendor shipments are branded shipments and exclude OEM sales for all vendors
</small>

Other manufacturers outside the top five include [[TCL Corporation|TCL Communication]], [[Lenovo]], [[Sony Mobile Communications]], [[Motorola Mobility|Motorola]].  Smaller current and past players include  Karbonn Mobile, [[Audiovox]] (now [[UTStarcom]]), [[BenQ-Siemens]], [[BlackBerry (company)|BlackBerry]], [[Casio]], [[CECT]], [[Coolpad]], [[Fujitsu]],  [[HTC]], [[Just5]], [[Kyocera]], [[Lumigon]], [[Micromax Mobile]], [[Mitsubishi Electric]], [[Modu]], [[NEC Corporation|NEC]], [[Neonode]], [[Openmoko]], [[Panasonic Corporation|Panasonic]], [[Palm Inc.|Palm]], [[Pantech Curitel|Pantech Wireless Inc.]], [[Philips]], [[Qualcomm|Qualcomm Inc.]], [[SAGEM Communication|Sagem]], [[Sanyo]], [[Sharp Corporation|Sharp]], [[Sierra Wireless]], [[SK Teletech]], Soutec, [[Trium]], [[Toshiba]], and Vidalco.

==Use of mobile phones==

===In general===
[[File:Mobile phone subscribers 1997-2014 ITU.svg|thumb|300px|Mobile phone subscribers per 100 inhabitants. <small>2014 figure is estimated.</small>]]
[[File:Colaba, Mumbai Cellphone Cellphone Repair Kiosk.jpg|thumb|A cellphone repair kiosk in [[Mumbai]], India]]

Mobile phones are used for a variety of purposes, including keeping in touch with family members, conducting business, and having access to a telephone in the event of an emergency. Some people carry more than one cell phone for different purposes, such as for business and personal use. Multiple SIM cards may also be used to take advantage of the benefits of different calling plans—a particular plan might provide cheaper local calls, long-distance calls, international calls, or roaming. The mobile phone has also been used in a variety of diverse contexts in society, for example:
* A study by [[Motorola]] found that one in ten cell phone subscribers have a second phone that often is kept secret from other family members. These phones may be used to engage in activities including extramarital affairs or clandestine business dealings.<ref>{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/1602044.stm |title=UK &#124; Millions keep secret mobile |publisher=BBC News |date=16 October 2001 |accessdate=4 November 2009}}</ref>
* Some organizations assist victims of domestic violence by providing mobile phones for use in emergencies. They are often refurbished phones.<ref>{{cite web|first=Richard |last=Brooks |url=http://www.pe.com/localnews/sbcounty/stories/PE_News_Local_S_helpphones13.3d74734.html |title=Donated cell phones help battered women &#124; San Bernardino County &#124; PE.com &#124; Southern California News &#124; News for Inland Southern California |publisher=The Press-Enterprise |date=13 August 2007 |accessdate=4 November 2009}}{{dead link|date=December 2013}}</ref>
* The advent of widespread text messaging has resulted in the [[cell phone novel]]; the first literary genre to emerge from the cellular age via [[text messaging]] to a website that collects the novels as a whole.<ref>{{cite web|last=Goodyear |first=Dana |url=http://www.newyorker.com/reporting/2008/12/22/081222fa_fact_goodyear |title=Letter from Japan: I ? Novels |publisher=The New Yorker |date=7 January 2009 |accessdate=29 July 2009}}</ref>
* [[Mobile telephony]] also facilitates activism and public journalism being explored by [[Reuters]] and [[Yahoo!]]<!--What does this sentence mean?--><ref>{{cite web|url=http://news.yahoo.com/you-witness-news |title=You Witness News |publisher=News.yahoo.com |date=26 January 2009 |accessdate=29 July 2009}}{{dead link|date=December 2013}}</ref> and small independent news companies such as Jasmine News in [[Sri Lanka]].

* The [[United Nations]] reported that mobile phones have spread faster than any other technology and can improve the livelihood of the poorest people in developing countries by providing access to information in places where [[landline]]s or the Internet are not available, especially in the [[least developed countries]]. Use of mobile phones also spawns a wealth of micro-enterprises, by providing work, such as selling airtime on the streets and repairing or refurbishing handsets.<ref>{{cite news| url=http://www.reuters.com/assets/print?aid=USTRE69D4XA20101014 | work=Reuters | first=Jonathan | last=Lynn | title=Mobile phones help lift poor out of poverty: U.N. study | accessdate=2013-12-03}}</ref>
* In [[Mali]] and other African countries, people used to travel from village to village to let friends and relatives know about weddings, births and other events, which are now avoided within mobile phone coverage areas, which is usually greater than land line penetration.
* The TV industry has recently started using mobile phones to drive live TV viewing through mobile apps, advertising, [[social tv]], and [[mobile TV]].<ref>{{cite web|url=http://www.tvgenius.net/blog/2011/01/31/4-ways-smartphones-save-tv/ |title=4 Ways Smartphones Can Save Live TV |publisher=Tvgenius.net |accessdate=4 June 2012}}{{dead link|date=December 2013}}</ref> 86% of Americans use their mobile phone while watching TV.
* In parts of the world, mobile phone sharing is common. It is prevalent in urban India, as families and groups of friends often share one or more mobiles among their members. There are obvious economic benefits, but often familial customs and traditional gender roles play a part.<ref>Donner, Jonathan, and Steenson, Molly Wright. "Beyond the Personal and Private: Modes of Mobile Phone Sharing in Urban India." In ''The Reconstruction of Space and Time: Mobile Communication Practices'', edited by Scott Campbell and Rich Ling, 231–250. Piscataway, NJ: Transaction Publishers, 2008.</ref> It is common for a village to have access to only one mobile phone, perhaps owned by a teacher or missionary, but available to all members of the village for necessary calls.<ref>Hahn, Hans and Kibora, Ludovic. "The Domestication of the Mobile Phone: Oral Society and New ICT in Burkina Faso". Journal of Modern African Studes 46 (2008): 87–109.</ref>

===Smartphones===
[[File:Active mobile broadband subscriptions 2007-2014.svg|thumb|300px|Active mobile broadband subscriptions per 100 inhabitants, from [http://www.itu.int/en/ITU-D/Statistics/Pages/stat/default.aspx ITU]]]
Smartphones have a number of distinguishing features but the [[ITU]] measures those with internet connection which it calls ''Active Mobile-Broadband subscriptions'' (which includes tablets etc.) In the developed world these have now overtaken the usage of earlier mobile systems but in the developing world account for only 20%.

===For distributing content===
In 1998, one of the first examples of [[content distribution|distributing and selling media content]] through the mobile phone was the sale of [[ringtone]]s by Radiolinja in Finland. Soon afterwards, other media content appeared such as news, video games, jokes, horoscopes, TV content and advertising. Most early content for mobile tended to be copies of legacy media, such as the banner advertisement or the TV news highlight video clip. Recently, unique content for mobile has been emerging, from the ringing tones and [[ringback tones]] in music to "mobisodes", video content that has been produced exclusively for mobile phones.

In 2006, the total value of mobile-phone-paid media content exceeded Internet-paid media content and was worth 31 billion dollars.<ref>source Informa 2007</ref> The value of music on phones was worth 9.3 billion dollars in 2007 and gaming was worth over 5 billion dollars in 2007.<ref>{{cite web|url=http://www.netsize.com/Ressources_Guide.htm |title=Downloads_Guide |publisher=Netsize |accessdate=29 July 2009}}</ref>

===While driving===
{{Main|Mobile phones and driving safety}}
[[File:Hand held phone in car.JPG|thumb|left|Texting in stop-and-go traffic in [[New York City]]]]

Mobile phone use while driving is common but controversial. Being distracted while operating a motor vehicle has been shown to increase the risk of accidents. Because of this, many jurisdictions prohibit the use of mobile phones while driving. Egypt, Israel, Japan, Portugal and Singapore ban both handheld and hands-free use of a mobile phone; others —including the UK, France, and many [[Restrictions on cell phone use by US drivers|U.S. states]]—ban handheld phone use only, allowing hands-free use.

Due to the increasing complexity of mobile phones, they are often more like mobile computers in their available uses. This has introduced additional difficulties for law enforcement officials in distinguishing one usage from another as drivers use their devices. This is more apparent in those countries which ban both handheld and hands-free usage, rather than those who have banned handheld use only, as officials cannot easily tell which function of the mobile phone is being used simply by looking at the driver. This can lead to drivers being stopped for using their device illegally on a phone call when, in fact, they were using the device for a legal purpose such as the phone's incorporated controls for car stereo or [[satnav]].

A recently published study has reviewed the incidence of mobile phone use while cycling and its effects on behaviour and safety.<ref>de Waard, D., Schepers, P., Ormel, W. and Brookhuis, K., 2010, ''Mobile phone use while cycling: Incidence and effects on behaviour and safety'', ''Ergonomics'', Vol 53, No. 1, January 2010, pp 30–42.</ref>

===Mobile banking and payments===
[[File:Mobile payment 01.jpg|thumb|Mobile payment system]]
{{main|Mobile banking|Mobile payment}}
{{see also|Branchless banking|Contactless payment}}
In many countries, mobile phones are used to provide [[mobile banking]] services, which may include the ability to transfer cash payments by secure SMS text message. Kenya's [[M-PESA]] mobile banking service, for example, allows customers of the mobile phone operator [[Safaricom]] to hold cash balances which are recorded on their SIM cards. Cash may be deposited or withdrawn from M-PESA accounts at Safaricom retail outlets located throughout the country, and may be transferred electronically from person to person as well as used to pay bills to companies.

[[Branchless banking]] has also been successful in South Africa and the Philippines. A pilot project in [[Bali]] was launched in 2011 by the [[International Finance Corporation]] and an [[Indonesia]]n bank [[Bank Mandiri]].<ref>{{cite web|url=http://www.thejakartapost.com/news/2011/03/01/branchless-banking-start-bali.html |title=Branchless banking to start in Bali |publisher=The Jakarta Post |date=13 April 2012 |accessdate=4 June 2012}}</ref>

Another application of mobile banking technology is [[Zidisha]], a US-based nonprofit micro-lending platform that allows residents of developing countries to raise small business loans from Web users worldwide. Zidisha uses mobile banking for loan disbursements and repayments, transferring funds from lenders in the United States to the borrowers in rural Africa using the Internet and mobile phones.<ref>{{cite web|url=http://www.microfinancefocus.com/news/2010/02/07/zidisha-set-to-expand-in-peer-to-peer-microfinance-julia-kurnia/ |title="Zidisha Set to "Expand" in Peer-to-Peer Microfinance", Microfinance Focus, Feb 2010 |publisher=Microfinancefocus.com |date=7 February 2010 |accessdate=4 June 2012}}{{dead link|date=December 2013}}</ref>

Mobile payments were first trialled in Finland in 1998 when two Coca-Cola vending machines in [[Espoo]] were enabled to work with SMS payments. Eventually, the idea spread and in 1999 the Philippines launched the country's first commercial mobile payments systems on the mobile operators [[Globe Telecom|Globe]] and [[Smart Communications|Smart]].

Some mobile phone can make [[mobile payment]]s via direct mobile billing schemes or through [[contactless payment]]s if the phone and [[point of sale]] support [[near field communication]] (NFC).<ref>{{cite web |url=http://www.banktech.com/blog/archives/2007/06/mobile_payments.html |title=Mobile Payments: Look to Korea |author= Feig, Nancy |publisher=banktech.com |date=25 June 2007| accessdate=29 January 2011}}{{dead link|date=June 2012}}</ref> This requires the co-operation of manufacturers, network operators and retail merchants to enable contactless payments through NFC-equipped mobile phones.<ref>{{cite news|url=http://www.dailymail.co.uk/sciencetech/article-1350709 |title=End of the credit card? With one swipe of an iPhone you'll be able to pay for your shopping |author= Poulter, Sean |publisher=dailymail.co.uk |date=27 January 2011 | accessdate=29 January 2011 |location=London}}</ref><ref>{{cite web |url=http://connectedplanetonline.com/mobile-apps/news/nfc-mobile-phone-explode-1110/ |title=NFC mobile phone set to explode |author= Ready, Sarah|publisher=connectedplanetonline.com |date=10 November 2009 | accessdate=29 January 2011}}</ref><ref>{{cite web |url=http://gigaom.com/mobile/visa-testing-nfc-memory-cards-for-wireless-payments/ |title=VISA Testing NFC Memory Cards for Wireless Payments |author= Tofel, Kevin C. |publisher=gigaom.com |date=20 August 2010 | accessdate=21 January 2011}}</ref>

===Tracking and privacy===
{{see also|Cellphone surveillance|Mobile phone tracking}}

Mobile phones are also commonly used to collect location data. While the phone is turned on, the geographical location of a mobile phone can be determined easily (whether it is being used or not), using a technique known as [[multilateration]] to calculate the differences in time for a signal to travel from the cell phone to each of several [[cell towers]] near the owner of the phone.<ref name="bbc-phone-locate">{{cite news|url= http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/technology/4738219.stm |title= Tracking a suspect by mobile phone |date= 3 August 2005 |work= BBC News |accessdate= 14 March 2009}}</ref><ref name="foxnews-phone-locate">{{cite news|url= http://www.foxnews.com/story/2009/03/18/cell-phone-tracking-can-locate-terrorists-but-only-where-it-legal/ |title= Cell Phone Tracking Can Locate Terrorists&nbsp;— But Only Where It's Legal |last= Miller |first= Joshua |date= 14 March 2009 |work= FOX News |accessdate= 4 February 2014}}</ref>

The movements of a mobile phone user can be tracked by their service provider and, if desired, by law enforcement agencies and their government. Both the [[SIM card]] and the handset can be tracked.<ref name="bbc-phone-locate"/>

China has proposed using this technology to track commuting patterns of Beijing city residents.<ref>{{cite news|url= http://voices.washingtonpost.com/posttech/2011/03/china_said_it_may_begin.html |author= Cecilia Kang |title= China plans to track cellphone users, sparking human rights concerns |publisher= The Washington Post |date= 3 March 2011}}</ref>  In the UK and US, law enforcement and intelligence services use mobiles to perform surveillance.  They possess technology to activate the microphones in cell phones remotely in order to listen to conversations that take place near the phone.<ref name="roving-bugs">{{cite news|url= http://news.cnet.com/FBI-taps-cell-phone-mic-as-eavesdropping-tool/2100-1029_3-6140191.html |title= FBI taps cell phone mic as eavesdropping tool |last= McCullagh |first= Declan |author2=Anne Broache |date= 1 December 2006 |work= CNet News |accessdate= 14 March 2009}}</ref><ref name="uk-mobile-bug">{{cite news|url= http://news.ft.com/cms/s/7166b8a2-02cb-11da-84e5-00000e2511c8.html |title= Use of mobile helped police keep tabs on suspect |last= Odell |first= Mark |date= 1 August 2005 |work= Financial Times |accessdate= 14 March 2009}}</ref>

===Thefts===
According to the [[Federal Communications Commission]], one out of three robberies involved the theft of a cellular phone.  Police data in San Francisco showed that one-half of all robberies in 2012 were thefts of cellular phones.  An online petition on [[Change.org]] called ''Secure our Smartphones'' urged smartphone manufacturers to install [[kill switch]]es in their devices to make them unusable in case of theft.  The petition is part of a joint effort by New York Attorney General [[Eric Schneiderman]] and San Francisco District Attorney [[George Gascon]] and was directed to the [[CEO]]s of the major smartphone manufacturers and telecommunication carriers.<ref>[http://www.sfexaminer.com/sanfrancisco/plea-urges-anti-theft-phone-tech/Content?oid=2447711  Adams, Mike "Plea Urges Anti-Theft Phone Tech"] ''San Francisco Examiner'' Friday, 7 June 2013 Page 5</ref>

On Monday, 10 June 2013, Apple announced it would install a kill switch on its next iPhone operating system, due to debut in October 2013.<ref>"Apple to add kill switches to help combat iPhone theft" by Jaxon Van Derbeken ''San  Francisco Chronicle'' Tuesday, 11 June 2013 Page 1</ref>

==Health effects==
{{Main|Mobile phone radiation and health}}
{{Further|Mobile phones on aircraft}}
The effect mobile phone radiation has on human health is the subject of recent interest and study, as a result of the enormous increase in mobile phone usage throughout the world. Mobile phones use [[electromagnetic radiation]] in the [[microwave]] range, which some believe may be harmful to human health. A large body of research exists, both [[epidemiology|epidemiological]] and experimental, in [[animal model|non-human animals]] and in humans, of which the majority shows no definite causative relationship between exposure to mobile phones and harmful biological effects in humans. This is often paraphrased simply as the balance of evidence showing no harm to humans from mobile phones, although a significant number of individual studies do suggest such a relationship, or are inconclusive. Other [[Wireless electronic devices and health|digital wireless systems]], such as data communication networks, produce similar radiation.

On 31 May 2011, the [[World Health Organization]] stated that mobile phone use may possibly represent a long-term health risk,<ref>{{cite web|title=IARC CLASSIFIES RADIOFREQUENCY ELECTROMAGNETIC FIELDS AS POSSIBLY CARCINOGENIC TO HUMANS|url=http://www.iarc.fr/en/media-centre/pr/2011/pdfs/pr208_E.pdf|work=World Health Organization}}</ref><ref name="World Health Organization">{{cite web |url= http://www.who.int/features/qa/30/en|title= What are the health risks associated with mobile phones and their base stations?|accessdate=19 January 2008|date= 5 December 2005|work= Online Q&A|publisher= [[World Health Organization]]}}</ref> classifying mobile phone radiation as "possibly carcinogenic to humans" after a team of scientists reviewed studies on cell phone safety.<ref name="cnnwhocarcinogenic">{{cite news |url= http://www.cnn.com/2011/HEALTH/05/31/who.cell.phones/index.html|title= WHO: Cell phone use can increase possible cancer risk|accessdate=31 May 2011|publisher=CNN|date=31 May 2011}}</ref> Mobile phones are in [[List of IARC Group 2B carcinogens|category 2B]], which ranks it alongside [[coffee]] and other possibly carcinogenic substances.<ref>[http://monographs.iarc.fr/ENG/Classification/ClassificationsGroupOrder.pdf Agents Classified by the IARC Monographs, Volumes 1–107]</ref><ref>{{cite journal|last=Kovvali|first=Gopala|title=Cell phones are as carcinogenic as coffee|journal=Journal of Carcinogenesis|date=1 January 2011|volume=10|issue=1|page=18|doi=10.4103/1477-3163.83044}}</ref>

At least some recent studies have found an association between cell phone use and certain kinds of brain and salivary gland tumors. Lennart Hardell and other authors of a 2009 meta-analysis of 11 studies from peer-reviewed journals concluded that cell phone usage for at least ten years "approximately doubles the risk of being diagnosed with a brain tumor on the same ('ipsilateral') side of the head as that preferred for cell phone use."<ref>{{cite journal|last=Khurana|first=VG|author2=Teo C |author3=Kundi M |author4=Hardell L |author5=Carlberg M |title=Cell phones and brain tumors: A review including the long term epidemiologic data|journal=Surgical Neurology|volume=72|issue=3|pages=205–214|doi=10.1016/j.surneu.2009.01.019|pmid=19328536|year=2009}}</ref>

One study of past cell phone use cited in the report showed a "40% increased risk for [[gliomas]] (brain cancer) in the highest category of heavy users (reported average: 30 minutes per day over a 10-year period)."<ref>{{cite web |url=http://www.businessinsider.com/cell-phones-cause-cancer-2011-5 |title=World Health Organization: Cell Phones May Cause Cancer|accessdate=31 May 2011|publisher=[[Business Insider]]}}</ref> This is a reversal from their prior position that cancer was unlikely to be caused by cellular phones or their base stations and that reviews had found no convincing evidence for other health effects.<ref name="World Health Organization" /><ref>{{cite web |url= http://www.who.int/mediacentre/factsheets/fs193/en|title= Electromagnetic fields and public health: mobile telephones and their base stations|accessdate=19 January 2008|date=June 2000|work= Fact sheet N°193|publisher= [[World Health Organization]]}}</ref> Certain countries, including France, have warned against the use of cell phones especially by minors due to health risk uncertainties.<ref>{{cite news|url=http://www.reuters.com/article/idUSL0223157720080102|title=France warns against excessive mobile phone use|accessdate=10 May 2010|date=2 January 2008|publisher=Reuters|author=Brian Rohan}}</ref> However, a study published 24 March 2012 in the ''[[British Medical Journal]]'' questioned these estimates, because the increase in brain cancers has not paralleled the increase in mobile phone use.<ref>{{cite journal | author=Little MP, Rajaraman P, Curtis RE, et al. | title = Mobile phone use and glioma risk: comparison of epidemiological study results with incidence trends in the United States | journal = BMJ | year = 2012 | volume=344 | pages=e1147 | doi = 10.1136/bmj.e1147 }}</ref>

==Future evolution==
{{Main|5G}}
5G is a technology used in research papers and projects to denote the next major phase of mobile telecommunication standards beyond the [[4G]]/[[IMT-Advanced]] standards. 5G is not officially used for any specification or official document yet made public by telecommunication companies or standardization bodies such as [[3GPP]], [[WiMAX]] Forum, or [[ITU-R]]. New standard releases beyond 4G are in progress by standardization bodies, but are at this time not considered as new mobile generations but under the 4G umbrella.

Deloitte is predicting a collapse in wireless performance to come as soon as 2016, as more devices using more and more services compete for limited bandwidth.<ref>[http://www.theregister.co.uk/2013/01/20/looming_spectrum_crunch/ "Wireless performance will collapse, prices rise: Deloitte."]</ref>

==Environmental impact==
{{Expand section|date=December 2011}}
{{see also|Mobile phone recycling}}
[[File:Sidewalk electronics repair in Hong Kong.JPG|thumb|right|300px|A mobile phone repair kiosk in [[Hong Kong]]]]
Studies have shown that around 40-50% of the environmental impact of a mobile phone occurs during the manufacturing of the printed wiring boards and integrated circuits.<ref>{{cite web|url=http://www.informinc.org/pages/media/the-secret-life-series/the-secret-life-of-cell-phones.html|title=The Secret Life Series - Environmental Impacts of Cell Phones|publisher=Inform, Inc.|accessdate=4 February 2014}}</ref> The average user replaces their mobile phone every 11 to 18 months.<ref>{{cite web|url=http://www.griffith.edu.au/engineering-information-technology/e-waste-research-group/facts-figures|title=E-waste research group, Facts and figures|publisher=Griffith University|accessdate=3 December 2011}}</ref> The discarded phones then contribute to [[electronic waste]].

Mobile phone manufacturers within [[Europe]] are subject to the [[Waste Electrical and Electronic Equipment Directive|WEEE directive]]. Australia introduced a mobile phone recycling scheme.<ref>{{cite web|url=http://www.arp.net.au/envcha.php|title=Mobile Phone Waste and The Environment|publisher=Aussie Recycling Program|accessdate=3 December 2011}}</ref>

==Conflict minerals==
{{See also|Conflict minerals}}
Demand for metals found in mobile phones is fuelling the [[Second Congo War|Congo Civil War]]. The war claimed almost 5.5 million lives.<ref>{{cite news |url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/africaandindianocean/democraticrepublicofcongo/8792068/Is-your-mobile-phone-helping-fund-war-in-Congo.html |title=Is your mobile phone helping fund war in Congo? |date= 27 September 2011 |work=The Daily Telegraph}}</ref> In a 2012 news story, ''The Guardian'' reported, "In unsafe mines deep underground in eastern Congo, [[Child labour|children are working]] to extract minerals essential for the electronics industry. The profits from the minerals finance the bloodiest conflict since the second world war; the war has lasted nearly 20 years and has recently flared up again. ... For the last 15 years, the [[Democratic Republic of the Congo]] has been a major source of natural resources for the mobile phone industry."<ref>{{cite news |url=http://www.theguardian.com/sustainable-business/blog/congo-child-labour-mobile-minerals |title= Children of the Congo who risk their lives to supply our mobile phones |date= 7 December 2012 |work=The Guardian}}</ref>

[[FairPhone]] is an attempt to develop a mobile phone which does not contain conflict minerals.

== See also ==
{{columns|col1=
* [[surveillance]]
* [[Cellular frequencies]]
* [[Customer proprietary network information]]
* [[Field telephone]]
* [[List of countries by number of mobile phones in use]]
* [[Mobile broadband]]
* [[Mobile Internet device]] (MID)
* [[Mobile phone accessories]]
* [[Form factor (mobile phones)|Mobile phone form factor]]
|col2=
* [[Nomophobia]]
* [[Optical head-mounted display]]
* [[OpenBTS]]
* [[Personal Handy-phone System]]
* [[Prepaid mobile phone]]
* [[Professional mobile radio]]
* [[Push-button telephone]]
* [[Rechargeable battery]]
* [[Tethering]]
* [[VoIP phone]]
|col3=
{{Portal |Telecommunication}}}}

==References==
{{reflist|30em}}

==Further reading==
<!-- alphabetical order please -->

{{Refbegin|30em}}
* Agar, Jon, ''Constant Touch: A Global History of the Mobile Phone'', 2004 ISBN 1-84046-541-7
* Ahonen, Tomi, ''m-Profits: Making Money with 3G Services'', 2002, ISBN 0-470-84775-1
* Ahonen, Kasper and Melkko, ''3G Marketing'' 2004, ISBN 0-470-85100-7
* {{cite journal |last=Fessenden |first=R. A. |authorlink= |year=1908 |title=Wireless Telephony |journal=Annual Report of the Board of Regents of the Smithsonian Institution |volume= |issue= |pages=161–196 |id= |url=http://books.google.com/?id=gtQWAAAAYAAJ&pg=PA161 |accessdate=7 August 2009 |quote= }}
* Glotz, Peter & Bertsch, Stefan, eds. ''Thumb Culture: The Meaning of Mobile Phones for Society'', 2005
* [[Gerard Goggin|Goggin, Gerard]], ''Global Mobile Media'' (New York: Routledge, 2011), p.&nbsp;176. ISBN 978-0415469180
* Jain, S. Lochlann. [http://joc.sagepub.com/cgi/reprint/2/3/385 "Urban Errands: The Means of Mobility"]. Journal of Consumer Culture 2:3 (November 2002) 385–404. {{doi|10.1177/146954050200200305}}.
* Katz, James E. & Aakhus, Mark, eds. ''Perpetual Contact: Mobile Communication, Private Talk, Public Performance'', 2002
* Kavoori, Anandam & Arceneaux, Noah, eds. ''The Cell Phone Reader: Essays in Social Transformation'', 2006
* Kennedy, Pagan. [http://www.nytimes.com/2013/03/17/magazine/who-made-that-cellphone.html?ref=technology Who Made That Cellphone?], ''[[The New York Times]]'', 15 March 2013, p. MM19
* Kopomaa, Timo. ''The City in Your Pocket'', Gaudeamus 2000
* [[Paul Levinson|Levinson, Paul]], ''Cellphone: The Story of the World's Most Mobile Medium, and How It Has Transformed Everything!'', 2004 ISBN 1-4039-6041-0
* Ling, Rich, ''The Mobile Connection: the Cell Phone's Impact on Society'', 2004 ISBN 1-55860-936-9
* Ling, Rich and Pedersen, Per, eds. ''Mobile Communications: Re-negotiation of the Social Sphere'', 2005 ISBN 1-85233-931-4
* [http://www.richardling.com/ Home page of Rich Ling]
* Nyíri, Kristóf, ed. ''Mobile Communication: Essays on Cognition and Community'', 2003
* Nyíri, Kristóf, ed. ''Mobile Learning: Essays on Philosophy, Psychology and Education'', 2003
* Nyíri, Kristóf, ed. ''Mobile Democracy: Essays on Society, Self and Politics'', 2003
* Nyíri, Kristóf, ed. ''A Sense of Place: The Global and the Local in Mobile Communication'', 2005
* Nyíri, Kristóf, ed. '' Mobile Understanding: The Epistemology of Ubiquitous Communication'', 2006
* [[Sadie Plant|Plant, Dr. Sadie]], [https://www.motorola.com/mot/doc/0/234_MotDoc.pdf ''on the mobile&nbsp;– the effects of mobile telephones on social and individual life'']{{dead link|date=June 2012}}, 2001
* [[Howard Rheingold|Rheingold, Howard]], ''Smart Mobs: The Next Social Revolution'', 2002 ISBN 0-7382-0861-2
* {{cite book|last= Singh |first=Rohit |title=Mobile phones for development and profit: a win-win scenario |publisher=Overseas Development Institute |date=April 2009 |page=2|url=http://www.odi.org.uk/resources/odi-publications/opinions/128-mobile-phones-business-development-private-sector.pdf}}
{{Refend}}

==External links==
{{Wiktionary}}
*{{Commons category-inline|Mobile phones}}
* {{HowStuffWorks|cell-phone|How Cell Phones Work}}
* [http://www.time.com/time/photogallery/0,29307,1636836_1389493,00.html "The Long Odyssey of the Cell Phone"], 15 photos with captions from ''Time'' magazine
* [http://www.cbc.ca/doczone/episodes/cellphone-a-ring-heard-around-the-world ''Cell Phone, the ring heard around the world'']—a video documentary by the [[Canadian Broadcasting Corporation]]
{{Mobile phones}}
{{Mobile telecommunications standards}}
{{Telephony}}
{{Telecommunications}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Mobile Phone}}
[[Category:Mobile phones| ]]
[[Category:1973 introductions]]
[[Category:Embedded systems]]
[[Category:Mobile telecommunications]]
[[Category:Mobile telecommunication services]]
[[Category:New media]]
[[Category:Telephony]]
[[Category:Videotelephony]]
	  </text>
      <sha1>b6uz5wwkljnmhrnptmtrs4tzb9wji8b</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  
   <page>
    <title>Kosher phone</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>18707</id>
    <revision>
      <id>5847450</id>
      <parentid>5843148</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-08-28T15:58:47Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>95.105.179.10</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment></comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">
		#REDIRECT [[Mobile phone#Kosher phones]]
	  </text>
      <sha1>b6uz5wwkljnmhrnptmtrs4tzb9wji8b</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  
     <page>
    <title>Mobilephone</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>18707</id>
    <revision>
      <id>5847450</id>
      <parentid>5843148</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-08-28T15:58:47Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>95.105.179.10</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment></comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">
		#REDIRECT [[Mobile phone]]
	  </text>
      <sha1>b6uz5wwkljnmhrnptmtrs4tzb9wji8b</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  
     <page>
    <title>Smartphone</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>18707</id>
    <revision>
      <id>5847450</id>
      <parentid>5843148</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-08-28T15:58:47Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>95.105.179.10</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment></comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">
		{{Redirect|Smartphones|the song by Trey Songz|SmartPhones (song)}}
[[File:Iphone-5s-black.png|thumb|The front and back of an [[iPhone 5S]] smartphone, launched in 2013]]
A '''smartphone''' (or '''smart phone''') is a [[mobile phone]] with more advanced computing capability and connectivity than basic [[feature phone]]s.<ref name="phonescoop-smartphone">{{cite web |url=http://www.phonescoop.com/glossary/term.php?gid=131 |title=Smartphone |publisher=''Phone Scoop'' |accessdate=2011-12-15}}</ref><ref name="phonescoop-featurephone">{{cite web |url=http://www.phonescoop.com/glossary/term.php?gid=310 |title=Feature Phone |publisher=''Phone Scoop'' |accessdate=2011-12-15}}</ref><ref>{{cite web |url=http://www.zdnet.com/blog/gadgetreviews/smartphone-vs-feature-phone-arms-race-heats-up-which-did-you-buy/6836 |title=Smartphone vs. feature phone arms race heats up; which did you buy? |author=Andrew Nusca |date=20 August 2009 |publisher=[[ZDNet]] |accessdate=2011-12-15}}</ref>Smartphones typically include the features of a computer with those of another popular consumer device, such as a [[personal digital assistant]], a [[portable media player|media player]], a [[digital camera]], and/or a [[GPS Phone|GPS navigation unit]]. Later smartphones include all of those plus the features of a [[touchscreen]] computer, including [[Web browser|web browsing]], [[Wi-Fi]], 3rd-party [[mobile app|apps]], [[motion sensor]] and [[mobile payment]].

Currently, about 84% of handset sales worldwide are for devices driven by [[Google|Google's]] [[Android (operating system)|Android]] with [[Apple Inc.|Apple's]] [[iOS]] [[mobile operating systems]] a distant second at around 12%.<ref name="ios-android-popular">{{cite news|title=Nokia revenues slide 24% but Lumia sales rise offers hope|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/technology/2013/jul/18/nokia-revenues-fall-lumia-sales?CMP=EMCNEWEML6619I2|accessdate=19 July 2013|newspaper=The Guardian|date=18 July 2013|author=Charles Arthur}}</ref><ref>{{cite web|title= Worldwide Smartphone Shipments Edge Past 300 Million Units in the Second Quarter; Android and iOS Devices Account for 96% of the Global Market, According to IDC |url=http://www.idc.com/getdoc.jsp?containerId=prUS25037214 |accessdate=4 September 2014|publisher=IDC |date=14 August 2014}}</ref>

==History==

===Early years===

<!-- Commented out because image was deleted: [[File:Paraskevakos_Smartphone_Prototype_(1971).jpg|thumb|right| Paraskevakos Prototype (1971<ref name=paraskevakos>U.S. Patent #3,812,296/5-21-1974 (''Apparatus for Generating and Transmitting Digital Information''), U.S. Patent #3,727,003/4-10-1973 (''Decoding and Display Apparatus for Groups of Pulse Trains''), U.S. Patent #3,842,208/10-15-1974 (''Sensor Monitoring Device'')</ref>)]] --> 
Devices that combined telephony and computing were first conceptualized by Theodore G. Paraskevakos in 1971 and patented in 1973, and were offered for sale beginning in 1993. He was the first to introduce the concepts of intelligence, data processing and visual display screens into telephones which gave rise to the "Smartphone." In 1971, Paraskevakos, working with [[Boeing]] in [[Huntsville, Alabama]], demonstrated a transmitter and receiver that provided additional ways to communicate with remote equipment, however it did not yet have general purpose [[PDA]] applications in a wireless device typical of smartphones.  They were installed at Peoples' Telephone Company in Leesburg, Alabama and were demonstrated to several telephone companies.   The original and historic working models are still in the possession of Paraskevakos.{{cn|date=September 2014}}

===Forerunners===

[[File:IBM Simon Personal Communicator.png|thumb|150px|upright|[[IBM Simon]] and charging base (1993<ref>{{cite web|title=Watch The Incredible 70-Year Evolution Of The Cell Phone|url=http://www.businessinsider.com/complete-visual-history-of-cell-phones-2011-5/1938-1#1993-13|work=Business Insider|publisher=Business Insider, Inc|accessdate=8 January 2014}}</ref>)]]

The first mobile phone to incorporate [[PDA]] features was an [[IBM]] prototype developed in 1992 and demonstrated that year at the [[COMDEX]] computer industry trade show. A refined version of the product was marketed to consumers in 1994 by [[BellSouth]] under the name [[IBM Simon|Simon Personal Communicator]]. The Simon was the first device that can be properly referred to as a "smartphone", even though that term was not yet coined.<ref name=bus_week_2012>{{cite web |url=http://www.businessweek.com/articles/2012-06-29/before-iphone-and-android-came-simon-the-first-smartphone |title=Before IPhone and Android Came Simon, the First Smartphone |last=Sager |first=Ira |date=2012-06-29 |publisher=Bloomberg L.P |work=Bloomberg Businessweek |accessdate=2012-06-30 |quote=Simon was the first smartphone. Twenty years ago, it envisioned our app-happy mobile lives, squeezing the features of a cell phone, pager, fax machine, and computer into an 18-ounce black brick.}}</ref><ref name=schneidawind>{{cite news |last=Schneidawind |first=John |title=Poindexter putting finger on PC bugs; Big Blue unveiling |date=1992-11-23 |newspaper=USA Today |page=2B}}</ref><ref name="BBC News">{{cite web|last1=Connelly|first1=Charlotte|title=World's first 'smartphone' celebrates 20 years|url=http://www.bbc.com/news/technology-28802053|website=BBC News|publisher=BBC News|accessdate=16 August 2014}}</ref> In addition to its ability to make and receive cellular phone calls, Simon was also able to send and receive [[faxes]] and e-mails and included several other apps like address book, calendar, appointment scheduler, calculator, world time clock, and note pad through its touch screen display. Simon is the first smartphone to be incorporated with the features of a PDA<ref>[http://www.spinfold.com/first-touchscreen-phone/ History of first touchscreen smartphone] Spinfold.com</ref>

The term "smart phone" appeared in print in 1995, for describing AT&T's "PhoneWriter(TM) Communicator" as a "smart phone".<ref name=ACM Interactions article>{{cite web |url=http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=208157 |title=Designing a GUI for Business Telephone users|last=Savage |first=Pamela |date=January 1995 |publisher=Association of Computing Machinery |accessdate=2014-09-13 |quote=...It is at this point that early usability test participants met impasse.  The switch connected to our "smart phone" is expecting the typical "dumb end-point"...  AT&T's PhoneWriter was demonstrated at the 1993 Comdex Computer Show...}}</ref>

===PDAs===

In the late 1990s, many mobile phone users carried a separate dedicated [[PDA]] device, running early versions of operating systems such as [[Palm OS]], [[BlackBerry OS]] or [[Windows CE]]/[[Pocket PC]].<ref name="phonescoop-smartphone"/> These operating systems would later evolve into [[mobile operating system]]s.

In 1996, [[Nokia]] released the [[Nokia 9000]]  which combined a [[personal digital assistant|PDA]] based on the [[GEOS V3.0]] operating system from [[Geoworks]] with a digital cellular phone based on the [[Nokia 2110]]. The two devices were fixed together via a hinge in what became known as a [[clamshell design]]. When opened, the display was on the inside top surface and with a physical [[QWERTY keyboard]] on the bottom. The personal organizer provided e-mail, calendar, address book, calculator and notebook with text-based web browsing, and the ability to send and receive faxes. When the personal organizer was closed, it could be used as a digital cellular phone.

In June 1999, [[Qualcomm]] released a "CDMA Digital PCS Smartphone" with integrated Palm PDA and Internet connectivity, known as the "pdQ Smartphone".<ref>{{cite web | url=http://www.qualcomm.com/media/releases/1999/06/15/qualcomm-s-pdq-smartphone-provides-ideal-platform-wireless-business | title=Qualcomm s pdQ Smartphone | publisher=''qualcomm.com''}}</ref>
 
In early 2000, the [[Ericsson R380]] was released by [[Ericsson Mobile Communications]],<ref>{{cite web | url=http://www.geek.com/hwswrev/pda/ericr380/ | title=PDA Review: Ericsson R380 Smartphone | publisher=''Geek.com'' | accessdate=27 April 2011}}</ref> and was the first device marketed as a "smartphone".<ref>{{cite web | url=http://www.mobilemag.com/2001/09/25/ericsson-introduces-the-new-r380e | title=Ericsson Introduces The New R380e | publisher=''Mobile Magazine'' | accessdate=27 April 2011}}</ref> It combined the functions of a mobile phone and a [[personal digital assistant]] (PDA), supported limited web browsing with a resistive touchscreen utilizing a stylus.<ref>{{cite news | url=http://www.pcmag.com/article2/0,2817,40827,00.asp | title=Ericsson R380 World Review & Rating | publisher=''PCMag.com'' | accessdate=27 April 2011}}</ref>

In early 2001, [[Palm, Inc.]] introduced the [[Kyocera 6035]], which combined a PDA with a mobile phone and operated on [[Verizon Wireless|Verizon]]. It also supported limited web browsing.<ref>{{cite web |url=http://www.palminfocenter.com/view_story.asp?ID=1707 |title=Kyocera QCP 6035 Smartphone Review |publisher=Palminfocenter.com |date=2001-03-16 |accessdate=2011-09-07}}</ref><ref>{{cite news |last=Segan |first=Sascha |url=http://www.pcmag.com/article2/0,2817,2361664,00.asp |title=Kyocera Launches First Smartphone In Years &#124; News & Opinion |publisher=PCmag.com |date=2010-03-23 |accessdate=2011-09-07}}</ref>

Smartphones before Android, iOS, and Blackberry, typically ran on [[Symbian]], which was originally developed by [[Psion]]. It was the world's most widely used smartphone operating system until Q4 2010.

===Mass adoption===

In 1999, the Japanese firm [[NTT Docomo]] released the first smartphones to achieve mass adoption within a country. These phones ran on [[i-mode]], which provided data transmission speeds up to 9.6 kbit/s.<ref>{{cite journal|last=Rose|first=Frank|title=Pocket Monster: How DoCoMo's wireless Internet service went from fad to phenom - and turned Japan into the first post-PC nation|journal=Wired|date=Sep 2001|volume=9|issue=9|url=http://www.wired.com/wired/archive/9.09/docomo_pr.html|accessdate=24 January 2014}}</ref> Unlike future generations of wireless services, [[NTT Docomo]]'s [[i-mode]] used [[cHTML]], a language which restricted some aspects of traditional [[HTML]] in favor of increasing data speed for the devices.  Limited functionality, small screens and limited bandwidth allowed for phones to maximize the slower data speeds available.<ref>{{cite book|last=Barnes, Stuart J|first=Huff, Sid L.|title=Rising Sun: iMode and the Wireless Internet|date=November 2003/Vol. 46, No. 1|publisher=Communications of the ACM|pages=79–84}}</ref>

The rise of [[i-mode]] helped [[NTT Docomo]] accumulate an estimated 40 million subscribers by the end of 2001.  It was also ranked first in market capitalization in Japan and second globally.  This power would wane in the face of the rise of 3G and new phones with advanced wireless network capabilities.<ref>{{cite web|last=Anwar|first=Sayid Tariq|title=NTT DoCoMo and M-Commerce: A Case Study in Market Expansion and Global Strategy|url=http://www.itu.dk/~rold/1_sem/B1/Cases/DoCoMo.pdf|publisher=The American Graduate School of International Management|accessdate=16 February 2014}}</ref>

Outside of Japan smartphones were still a rare feature, although throughout the mid-2000s, devices based on Microsoft's [[Windows Mobile]] started to gain high popularity among businessmen and businesswomen in the U.S. The [[BlackBerry]] later gained mass adoption in the U.S., which in 2006 popularized the term CrackBerry due to its addictive nature.<ref>{{cite news|title=Info Addicts Are All Thumbs: Crackberry Is the 2006 Word of the Year|url=http://www.prnewswire.com/news-releases/websters-new-worldr-college-dictionary-info-addicts-are-all-thumbs-55824847.html|accessdate=24 January 2014|newspaper=PR Newswire|date=Nov 1, 2006}}</ref> The company first released its GSM BlackBerry 6210, BlackBerry 6220, & BlackBerry 6230 devices in 2003.  Also released was the Blackberry 7730 which featured a color screen.<ref>{{cite web|last=Halevy|first=Ron|title=The History of RIM & the BlackBerry Smartphone, Part 3: The Evolution Of Color|url=http://www.berryreview.com/2009/03/16/the-history-of-rim-the-blackberry-smartphone-part-3-the-evolution-of-color/|accessdate=16 February 2014}}</ref> In 2006 and 2007, both operating systems were in a large lead in the North American market, although while BlackBerry was popular among both business people and young people, Windows Mobile was only popular in the former.

These successive waves of phone technology allowed users to email, fax and make traditional calls, making it a useful tool for business travelers. As the Blackberry gained customers, less sophisticated users were attracted to its many communication options.

In Europe, Windows Mobile was never a large player in the market, and BlackBerry didn't make a notable impact in the market until around 2008. Symbian was the most popular smartphone OS in Europe during the mid and late 2000s. This was largely led by Nokia, which has always been a popular brand outside of North America. Initially Nokia's Symbian devices were focused on business, the same way as Windows Mobile and BlackBerry devices at the time. From 2006 onwards, Nokia started to make entertainment-focused smartphones, which were popularized by the Nseries. The N95, for instance, had breakthrough multimedia features for its time, and marked the start of a broader market of smartphones within younger people, and not just business. In Asia (except Japan), the trend was similar to Europe's.

Another company that made a breakthrough was the Palm. Although originally PDAs, Palms later turned into business-focused smartphones, largely competing with BlackBerry and Windows Mobile in the U.S. market, and was less popular in Europe and Asia.

All leaders of the 2000s suffered following the release of the iPhone.

===iPhone & Android===

In 2007, [[Apple Inc.]] introduced the [[iPhone (original)|iPhone]], one of the first mobile phones to use a [[multi-touch]] interface. The iPhone was notable for its use of a large touchscreen for direct finger input as its main means of interaction, instead of a [[Stylus (computing)|stylus]], keyboard, or keypad typical for smartphones at the time.<ref name="iPhone-is-not">{{cite web |url=http://www.engadget.com/2007/01/09/the-iphone-is-not-a-smartphone/ |title=The iPhone is not a smartphone |date=9 January 2007 |accessdate=11 July 2010|publisher=Engadget.com}}</ref> 2008 saw the release of the first phone to use [[Android (operating system)|Android]] called the [[HTC Dream]] (also known as the T-Mobile G1).<ref name="UK release of T-Mobile G1"/><ref name="T-Mobile G1 Event Round-up"/> Android  is an [[open source|open-source]] platform founded by Andy Rubin and backed by [[Google]].<ref name="open-alliance">{{cite web
 |url= http://www.openhandsetalliance.com/oha_members.html
 |title=Alliance Members
 |work=Open Handset Alliance
 |accessdate=16 January 2011
}}</ref><ref name="android-atlas">[http://www.cnet.com/android-atlas/ The Android Atlas] Cnet.com. Retrieved 21 August 2013.</ref> Although Android's adoption was relatively slow at first, it started to gain widespread popularity in 2010, and now dominates the market.

Both of these platforms led to the drop of the previous leading companies. Microsoft, for instance, started a new OS from scratch, in the form of [[Windows Phone]], which is now the third largest OS. Nokia abandoned Symbian and partnered with Microsoft to use Windows Phone on its smartphones. Palm was bought by [[Hewlett-Packard]], turned into [[webOS]], and later demised. BlackBerry also made a new system from scratch, [[BlackBerry 10]].

The iPhone also had a knock-on effect on smartphone form factors. Before 2007 it was common for devices to have a numeric keypad or [[QWERTY]] keyboard in either a candybar or sliding form factor. However, by 2010, there were no top-tier smartphones with numeric keypads. {{As of|2014}}, [[BlackBerry Limited]] – with a 0.6% share of the market in Q4 2013<ref name="2014 market share"/> – is the sole remaining brand of high-end smartphones with physical keyboards.

===The future===

In 2013, the [[Fairphone]] company launched its first "socially ethical" smartphone at the [[London Design Festival]] to address concerns regarding the sourcing of materials in the manufacturing.<ref name="Fair">{{cite news|title=Why is Apple so shifty about how it makes the iPhone?|url=http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2013/sep/23/apple-shifty-about-making-iphone?CMP=EMCNEWEML6619I2&et_cid=50104&et_rid=7107573&Linkid=http%3a%2f%2fwww.theguardian.com%2fcommentisfree%2f2013%2fsep%2f23%2fapple-shifty-about-making-iphone|accessdate=24 September 2013|newspaper=The Guardian|date=23 September 2013|author=George Monbiot}}</ref> In late 2013,  QSAlpha commenced production of a smartphone designed entirely around security, encryption and identity protection.<ref>{{cite web|title=Quasar IV Encrypted Ninja Smartphone Goes Into Production, Despite Indiegogo Failure|url=http://techcrunch.com/2013/10/09/quasar-iv-encrypted-ninja-smartphone-goes-into-production-despite-indiegogo-failure/?ncid=tcdaily|work=TechCrunch|publisher=AOL Inc|accessdate=10 October 2013|author=Darrell Etherington|date=10 October 2013}}</ref> In December 2013, the world's first curved-[[OLED]] technology smartphones were introduced to the retail market with the sale of the Samsung Galaxy Round and LG G Flex models.<ref>{{cite news|title=Bendable smartphones aren't coming anytime soon|url=http://www.smh.com.au/digital-life/mobiles/bendable-smartphones-arent-coming-anytime-soon-20131213-2zbtq.html|accessdate=26 December 2013|newspaper=The Sydney Morning Herald|date=16 December 2013|author=Ian King}}</ref>

Foldable [[OLED]] smartphones could be as much as a decade away because of the cost of producing them. There is a relatively high failure rate when producing these screens. As little as a speck of dust can ruin a screen during production. Creating a battery that can be folded is another hurdle.<ref>[http://www.smh.com.au/digital-life/mobiles/bendable-smartphones-arent-coming-anytime-soon-20131213-2zbtq.html Bendable smartphones aren't coming anytime soon], The Sydney Morning Herald, Ian King, 16 December 2013</ref> Samsung fully foldable phones are expected around 2016 to 2017.<ref>[http://news.yahoo.com/samsung-phone-bended-display-may-160221151.html Samsung Phone With Bended Display May Come This Year], LAPTOP, 11 February 2014, Lisa Eadicicco</ref>

A clear thin layer of crystal glass can be added to small screens like watches and smartphones that make them solar powered. Smartphones could gain 15% more battery life during a typical day. The first smartphones using this technology should arrive in 2015. This screen can also work to receive [[Li-Fi]] signals and so can the smartphone camera.<ref>[http://motherboard.vice.com/blog/the-internet-of-light-the-first-li-fi-smartphone-debuts-at-ces An Internet of Light: Going Online with LEDs and the First Li-Fi Smartphone], Motherboard Beta, Brian Merchant</ref> The cost of these screens per smartphone is between $2 and $3, much cheaper than most new technology.<ref>[http://www.digitaltrends.com/mobile/wysips-solar-charging-screen-li-fi-impressions/ Your next phone may charge and receive data through this incredible screen], Digital Trends, 19 January 2014, Jeffrey Van Camp</ref>

Near future smartphones might not have a traditional battery as their sole source of power. Instead, they may pull energy from radio, television, cellular or Wi-Fi signals.<ref>[http://www.nytimes.com/2014/02/03/technology/building-a-better-battery.html?partner=yahoofinance&_r=1 Building a Better Battery], NY Times, 2 February 2014, BRIAN X. CHEN and NICK BILTON</ref>

In early 2014, smartphones are beginning to use [[Quad HD]] (2K) 2560x1440 on 5.5" screens with up to 534 [[Pixel density|ppi]] on devices such as the [[LG G3]] which is a significant improvement over Apple's [[retina display]]. Quad HD is used in advanced televisions and computer monitors, but with 110 ppi or less on such larger displays.<ref>{{cite web |url=http://www.engadget.com/2014/02/18/do-you-really-need-a-4k-smartphone-screen/ |title=Do you really need a 4K smartphone screen? |author=Steve Dent |date=February 18, 2014}}</ref>

In 2014, Wi-Fi will continue to become the primary network for smartphones.  As these devices do more and more with data and Wi-Fi becomes more prevalent and easier to connect to, Wi-Fi First smartphones service will start to take off.<ref>[http://www.wired.com/insights/2014/01/collision-course-wi-fi-first-role-changing-mobile-communications/], Wired, 8 January 2014, Alan Berrey</ref><ref>[http://www.lightreading.com/mobile/carrier-wifi/why-wifi-first-works-for-wireless/d/d-id/707117], LightReading, 30 December 2013, Sarah Reddy</ref><ref>[http://www.pcmag.com/article2/0,2817,2425853,00.asp], PC Mag, 16 October 2013, Stephanie Mlot</ref>

Since 2013, water and dustproofing have made their way into mainstream high end smartphones instead of specialist models with the [[Sony Xperia Z]] continuing through the [[Sony Xperia Z2]] and also from other manufacturers with the [[Samsung Galaxy S5]].<ref>{{cite web |url=http://en.tempo.co/read/news/2014/03/01/240558504/Sony-Xperia-Z2-Ready-to-Compete-With-Samsung-Galaxy-S5 |title=Sony Xperia Z2 Ready to Compete With Samsung Galaxy S5 |author=Rindu P Hestya |date=March 1, 2014}}</ref>

==Mobile operating systems==
{{Main|Mobile operating system}}

===Android===
{{Main|Android (operating system)}}
[[File:Android 4.4.2.png|thumb|100px|Android 4.4.2 home screen]]
[[Android (operating system)|''Android'']] is an [[open source|open-source]] platform founded in October 2003 by Andy Rubin and backed by [[Google]], along with major hardware and software developers (such as [[Intel]], [[HTC Corporation|HTC]], [[ARM Holdings|ARM]], [[Motorola]] and [[Samsung]]) that form the [[Open Handset Alliance]].<ref name="open-alliance" /><ref name="android-atlas"/> In October 2008, [[HTC]] released the [[HTC Dream]], the first phone to use Android.<ref name="UK release of T-Mobile G1">{{cite press release|url=http://www.opt-development.co.uk/press-office/release.php?id=242 |title=T-Mobile G1 Hits the UK|publisher=[[T-Mobile]] UK |date=30 October 2008}}</ref><ref name="T-Mobile G1 Event Round-up">{{cite press release|url=http://www.talkandroid.com/260-t-mobile-g1-details |title=T-Mobile G1 Event Round-up|publisher=[[Talk Media Inc.]] US |date=22 October 2008}}</ref> The software suite included on the phone consists of integration with Google's proprietary applications, such as [[Google Maps|Maps]], [[Google Calendar|Calendar]], and [[Gmail]], and a full HTML web browser. Android supports the execution of native applications and third-party apps which are available via [[Google Play]], which launched in October 2008 as [[Android Market]]. By Q4 2010, Android became the best-selling smartphone platform.<ref>{{cite news|url=http://gigaom.com/2010/08/02/android-sales-overtake-iphone-in-the-u-s/ |title=Android sales overtake iPhone in the US|publisher=Gigaom| date=2 August 2010}}</ref>
{{-}}
===iOS===
{{Main|iOS}}
[[File:IPhone 2G PSD Mock.png|thumb|upright|100px|The original [[iPhone]] (2007)]]
In 2007, [[Apple Inc.]] introduced the [[iPhone (original)|iPhone]], one of the first mobile phones to use a [[multi-touch]] interface. The iPhone was notable for its use of a large touchscreen for direct finger input as its main means of interaction, instead of a [[Stylus (computing)|stylus]], keyboard, or keypad as typical for smartphones at the time.<ref name="iPhone-is-not"/> In July 2008, Apple introduced its second generation [[iPhone 3G|iPhone]] with a much lower list price and 3G support. Simultaneously, they introduced the [[App Store (iOS)|App Store]], which allowed any iPhone to install third-party native applications. Featuring over 500 applications at launch,<ref>{{cite web |url=http://www.apple.com/pr/library/2008/07/10iphone.html |title=iPhone 3G on Sale Tomorrow |date=2008-07-10 |publisher=Apple Inc. |work=Press Release |accessdate=2009-01-17}}</ref> the App Store eventually achieved 1 billion downloads in the first year, and 15 billion by 2011.<ref>{{cite web |url=http://www.apple.com/pr/library/2009/07/14Apples-App-Store-Downloads-Top-1-5-Billion-in-First-Year.html |title=Apple’s App Store Downloads Top 1.5 Billion in First Year |date=July 14, 2009 |publisher=Apple Inc. |work=Press Release |accessdate=2011-12-15}}</ref><ref>{{cite web |url=http://www.apple.com/pr/library/2011/07/07Apples-App-Store-Downloads-Top-15-Billion.html |title=Apple's App Store Downloads Top 15 Billion |work=Press Release |date=July 7, 2011 |publisher=Apple Inc. |accessdate=2011-12-15}}</ref>
{{-}}
===Windows Phone===
{{main|Windows Phone}}

In February 2010, Microsoft unveiled [[Windows Phone 7]] with a [[User Interface]] inspired by Microsoft's "[[Metro Design Language]]", to replace Windows Mobile. Windows Phone 7 integrates with Microsoft services such as [[SkyDrive|Microsoft SkyDrive]], [[Microsoft Office Mobile|Office]], [[Xbox]] and [[Microsoft Bing|Bing]], as well as non-Microsoft services such as [[Facebook]], [[Twitter]] and [[Google Account|Google accounts]]. This software platform runs the [[Microsoft Mobile]] smartphones, and has received some positive reception from the technology press and been praised for its uniqueness and differentiation.<ref>{{cite web |url= http://www.engadget.com/2010/02/15/windows-phone-7-series-is-official-and-microsoft-is-playing-to/ |title=Windows Phone 7 Series is official, and Microsoft is playing to win |publisher=Engadget |date=2010-02-15 |accessdate=2011-09-07}}</ref><ref>{{cite web|author=Matt Buchanan |url=http://gizmodo.com/5471805/windows-phone-7-series-everything-is-different-now |title=Windows Phone 7 Series: Everything Is Different Now |publisher=Gizmodo.com |date=2010-02-15 |accessdate=2011-09-07}}</ref><ref>{{cite web|author=Devin Coldewey |url=http://www.crunchgear.com/2010/02/15/windows-phone-7-series-our-take/ |title=Windows Phone 7 Series: Our Take &#124; TechCrunch |publisher=Crunchgear.com |date=2010-02-15 |accessdate=2011-09-07}}</ref>

===Firefox OS===
{{main|Firefox OS}}

Firefox OS (originally called the ''boot to gecko'' project) was demonstrated by [[Mozilla]] in February 2012. It was designed to have a complete community based alternative system for mobile devices, using open standards and HTML5 applications. The first commercially available Firefox OS phones were ZTE Open and Alcatel One Touch Fire. As of 2014 more companies have partnered with Mozilla including Panasonic (which is making a smart TV with Firefox OS) and Sony.<ref>{{cite web|author=Feb 26 2013 |url=http://www.mozillaphilippines.org/sony-mobile-plans-to-release-firefox-os-devices-by-2014/ |title=Sony Mobile Plans to Release Firefox OS Devices by 2014 |publisher=Mozilla Philippines |date=2013-02-25 |accessdate=2014-06-17}}</ref>

===Tizen===
{{main|Tizen}}
'''Tizen''' is a [[Linux kernel|Linux]]-based [[operating system]] for devices, including smartphones, [[tablet computer|tablets]], [[In car entertainment|in-vehicle infotainment]] (IVI) devices, [[smart TV]]s, [[laptop]]s and smart cameras. Tizen is a project within the [[Linux Foundation]] and is governed by a Technical Steering Group (TSG) composed of [[Samsung]] and [[Intel]] among others.

In April 2014, Samsung released the Samsung Gear 2 and the Gear 2 Neo, running Tizen.<ref>{{cite web | title=Samsung's wrist reboot: Gear 2 and Gear 2 Neo unveiled | author=Techradar | url=http://www.techradar.com/au/news/portable-devices/samsung-s-tizen-smartwatch-to-drop-galaxy-branding-galaxy-gear-2-also-leaked-1227419 | publisher=Techradar | date=2014-02-23 | accessdate=2014-02-23}}</ref>

===Sailfish OS===
{{main|Sailfish OS}}

The Sailfish OS is based on the [[Linux kernel]] and [[Mer (software distribution)|Mer]].<ref>{{cite web|first=Sailfish OS community|title=The Sailfish OS Wiki|url=https://sailfishos.org/wiki/Main_Page#Contribute|work=The Sailfish OS Wiki|accessdate=14 March 2013}}</ref> Additionally Sailfish OS includes a partially or completely [[proprietary software|proprietary]] multi-tasking [[user interface]] programmed by [[Jolla]]. This user interface differentiate Jolla smartphones from others.<ref>{{cite web | title = Jolla OS Will Run Android Apps Says CEO Jussi Hurmola | url = http://www.ibtimes.co.uk/articles/375368/20120820/jolla-os-running-android-apps-jussi-hurmola.htm}}</ref> Sailfish OS is intended to be a system made by  many of the MeeGo team, which left [[Nokia]] to form Jolla, utilizing funding from Nokia's "Bridge" program which helps establish and support start-up companies formed by ex-Nokia employees.<ref>{{citation | url = http://www.hs.fi/english/article/Many+former+Nokia+employees+start+businesses+of+their+own/1329104331230 | title = Many former Nokia employees start businesses of their own | newspaper = Helsingin Sanomat}}</ref><ref>{{cite web|last=Lunden|first=Ingrid|title=Nokia Bridge: Nokia’s Incubator Gives Departing Employees €25k And More To Pursue Ideas That Nokia Has Not|url=http://techcrunch.com/2012/07/10/nokia-bridge-nokias-incubator-gives-departing-employees-e25k-and-more-to-pursue-ideas-that-nokia-has-not/|work=techcrunch.com|publisher=techcrunch.com|accessdate=7 June 2013}}</ref><ref>{{cite web|last=Tung|first=Liam|title=Inside Nokia Bridge: How Nokia funds ex-employees' new start-ups|url=http://www.zdnet.com/inside-nokia-bridge-how-nokia-funds-ex-employees-new-start-ups-7000000863/|work=zdnet.com|publisher=© 2013 CBS Interactive|accessdate=7 June 2013}}</ref>

===BlackBerry===
{{main|BlackBerry}}
[[File:Blackberry 8900 ColorIsOff.jpg|thumb|100px|[[BlackBerry Curve]] 8900 (2008)]]
In 1999, [[Research In Motion|RIM]] released its first [[BlackBerry]] devices, providing secure real-time push-email communications on wireless devices. Services such as BlackBerry Messenger provide the integration of all communications into a single inbox. There are 80 million active BlackBerry service subscribers and the 200 millionth BlackBerry smartphone was shipped in September 2012.<ref>[http://www.rim.com/investors/documents/pdf/financial/2011/Q1_financial_information.pdf 100 millionth BlackBerry smartphone shipped in June 2010]</ref> Most recently, RIM has undergone a platform transition, changing its name to BlackBerry and making new devices on a new platform named "BlackBerry 10."<ref>{{cite web |author=Kevin McLaughlin |url=http://www.crn.com/news/client-devices/222002587/blackberry-users-call-for-rim-to-rethink-service.htm |title=BlackBerry Users Call For RIM To Rethink Service |publisher=CRN.com |date=December 17, 2009 |accessdate=2011-12-15}}</ref>
{{-}}
===Symbian===
{{Main|Symbian}}
[[File:Nokia N8 (front view).jpg|thumb|100px|[[Nokia N8]] (2010)]]
Symbian was originally developed by [[Psion]] as [[EPOC32]]. It was the world's most widely used smartphone operating system until Q4 2010, though the platform never gained popularity or widespread awareness in the U.S., as it did in Europe and Asia. The first Symbian phone, the touchscreen [[Ericsson R380|Ericsson R380 Smartphone]], was released in 2000,<ref>{{cite web |url=http://www.geek.com/hwswrev/pda/ericr380/ |title=PDA Review: Ericsson R380 Smartphone |publisher=''Geek.com'' |accessdate=2011-12-15}}</ref><ref>{{cite web |url=http://www.i-symbian.com/wp-content/uploads/2009/11/Symbian_Evolution.pdf |format=PDF |title= Symbian Device – The OS Evolution |publisher=''Independent Symbian Blog'' |accessdate=2011-12-15}}</ref> and was the first device marketed as a "smartphone".<ref>{{cite web |url=http://www.mobilemag.com/2001/09/25/ericsson-introduces-the-new-r380e |title=Ericsson Introduces The New R380e |publisher=''Mobile Magazine'' |accessdate=2011-12-15}}</ref> It combined a PDA with a mobile phone.<ref>{{cite news |url=http://www.pcmag.com/article2/0,2817,40827,00.asp |title=Ericsson R380 World, Review & Rating |publisher=''PCMag.com'' |accessdate=2011-12-15 |first=Bruce |last=Brown}}</ref> In February 2011, Nokia announced that it would replace Symbian with [[Windows Phone]] as the operating system on all of its future smartphones, with the platform getting abandoned throughout the following few years.<ref name="NokiaWinPho7">{{cite news |agency=Associated Press |url=http://www.cbc.ca/news/technology/story/2011/02/11/nokia-microsoft-smart-phone-apple-google.html |title=Nokia, Microsoft in pact to rival Apple, Google – Technology & Science |publisher=CBC.ca |date=2011-02-11 |accessdate=2011-12-15}}</ref>
{{-}}
===Windows Mobile===
{{main|Windows Mobile}}
[[File:HTC kaiser smartphone2.jpg|file|thumb|100px|[[HTC Kaiser]] (2009)]]
Windows Mobile was based on the [[Windows CE]] kernel and first appeared as the Pocket PC 2000 operating system. Throughout its lifespan, the operating system was available in both touchscreen and non-touchscreen formats. It was supplied with a suite of applications developed with the Microsoft Windows API and was designed to have features and appearance somewhat similar to desktop versions of Windows. Third parties could develop software for Windows Mobile with no restrictions imposed by Microsoft. Software applications were eventually purchasable from Windows Marketplace for Mobile during the service's brief lifespan. Windows mobile was phased out in favor of Windows Phone.
{{-}}
===Palm OS===
[[File:Treo650-Sprint.png|100px|thumb|[[Palm Treo]] 650 (2004)]]
{{main|Palm OS}}
In late 2001, Handspring launched their own Springboard GSM phone module with limIn. Early 2002, [[Handspring (company)|Handspring]] released the [[Palm OS]] [[Palm Treo|Treo]] smartphone with both a touch screen and a full keyboard. The Treo had wireless web browsing, email, calendar, a contact organizer and mobile third-party applications that could be downloaded or synced with a computer.<ref>{{cite web |url=http://www.businessweek.com/bwdaily/dnflash/nov2001/nf20011129_0157.htm |author=Stephen H. Wildstrom |title=Handspring's Breakthrough Hybrid |publisher=Businessweek.com |date=November 30, 2001 |accessdate=2011-12-15}}</ref> Handspring was soon acquired by Palm, which released the Treo 600 and continued, though the series eventually took on Windows Mobile. After buying [[Palm, Inc]], in 2011 [[Hewlett-Packard]] (HP) finally discontinued its smartphones and tablets  production using [[webOS]] which is initial developed by Palm, Inc.<ref>{{cite web |url=http://www.brighthand.com/default.asp?newsID=18078&news=HP+webOS+Palm+RIM |title=HP To Stop Making webOS Smartphones, Might License the OS to Others |accessdate=November 26, 2013}}</ref>
{{-}}
===Bada===
{{main|Bada}}
The Bada operating system for smartphones was announced by Samsung in November 2009.<ref>{{cite news |title=Samsung Bailing on Windows Mobile |newspaper=[[InformationWeek]] |author=Ed Hansberry |date=11 November 2009 |url=http://www.informationweek.com/blog/main/archives/2009/11/samsung_bailing.html}}</ref><ref>{{cite news |title=Samsung to Discard Windows Phone |newspaper=Telecoms Korea |date=9 November 2009 |url=http://www.telecomskorea.com/market-8281.html}}</ref> The first Bada-based phone was the [[Samsung S8500|Samsung Wave S8500]], released in June 2010.<ref>{{cite news |title=Samsung Wave, first Bada smartphone hits the market |url=http://www.bada.com/samsung-wave-first-bada-smartphone-hits-the-market/ |work=Bada |date=24 May 2010 |accessdate=3 February 2011}}</ref><ref>{{cite web|url=http://badawave.com/ |title=BadaWave |publisher=BadaWave |accessdate=2012-01-05}}</ref><ref>{{cite web |url=http://www.theinquirer.net/inquirer/news/1722287/samsung-waves-away-million |title=Samsung Waves away a million |date=13 July 2010 |publisher=[[The Inquirer]]}}</ref> Samsung shipped 4.5  million phones running Bada in Q2 of 2011.<ref>{{cite web |url=http://www.pocketgamer.co.uk/r/PG.Biz/asymco+news/news.asp?c=32049 |title=Samsung Bada shipments up 355% to 4.5 million units in Q2 2011 &#124; asymco news &#124; PG.Biz |publisher=Pocket Gamer |accessdate=2011-09-07}}</ref> In 2013, Bada merged with a similar platform called [[Tizen]].
{{-}}

==Application stores==
{{Main|List of digital distribution platforms for mobile devices}}

The introduction of Apple's [[App Store (iOS)|App Store]] for the iPhone and iPod Touch in July 2008 popularized manufacturer-hosted [[list of digital distribution platforms for mobile devices|online distribution]] for third-party applications ([[software]], [[computer programs]]) focused on a single platform. Up until that point, smartphone application distribution depended on [[List of digital distribution platforms for mobile devices#Third-party platforms|third-party sources]] providing applications for multiple platforms, such as [[GetJar]], [[Handango]], [[Handmark]], and [[PocketGear]].

Following the success of the App Store, other smartphone manufacturers launched application stores, such as [[Google]]'s [[Android Market]] in October 2008 and [[Research In Motion|RIM]]'s [[BlackBerry App World]] in April 2009.

==Market share==

===Smartphone usage===

In the third quarter of 2012, one billion smartphones were in use worldwide.<ref>{{cite web|title=Worldwide smartphone user base hits 1 billion|url=http://news.cnet.com/8301-1035_3-57534132-94/worldwide-smartphone-user-base-hits-1-billion/|work=CNet|publisher=CBS Interactive, Inc|accessdate=26 July 2013|author=Don Reisinger|date=17 October 2012}}</ref> Global smartphone sales surpassed the sales figures for features phones in early 2013.<ref name="news1">{{cite news| url= http://www.3news.co.nz/Smartphones-now-outsell-dumb-phones/tabid/412/articleID/295878/Default.aspx|work=3 News NZ |title= Smartphones now outsell 'dumb' phones| date=April 29, 2013}}</ref> As of 2013, 65 percent U.S. mobile consumers own smartphones.<ref>{{cite web |url=http://www.engadget.com/2014/02/11/two-thirds-of-americans-now-have-smartphones/ |title=Two-thirds of Americans now have smartphones |author=Jon Fingas |date=February 11, 2014}}</ref> The European mobile device market as of 2013 is 860 million.<ref>{{cite web|title=European Mobile Market|url=http://www.telecomsmarketresearch.com/resources/Mobile_Market_Europe.shtml|work=telecoms market research|publisher=CMSinfo|accessdate=27 June 2013|year=2011}}</ref>  In China, smartphones represented more than half of all handset shipments in the second quarter of 2012.<ref>{{cite web |url=http://blogs.ft.com/beyond-brics/2012/08/24/apple-in-china-not-as-cool-as-before/ |title=Apple in China: not as cool as before |author=beyondbrics |date=2012-08-24|accessdate= 2012-08-30|work= [[ft.com]]}}</ref>

As of November 2011, 27% of all photographs were taken with camera-equipped smartphones.<ref>{{cite web|title=Smartphones killing point-and-shoots, now take almost 1/3 of photos|url=http://gigaom.com/2011/12/22/smartphones-killing-point-and-shoots-now-take-almost-13-of-photos/|work=GIGAOM|publisher=GIGAOM|accessdate=27 June 2013|author=Erica Ogg|date=22 December 2011}}</ref> A study conducted in September 2012 concluded that 4 out of 5 smartphone owners use the device to shop.<ref>{{cite web|title=comScore: 4 Out Of 5 Smartphone Owners Use Device To Shop; Amazon Is The Most Popular Mobile Retailer|url=http://techcrunch.com/2012/09/19/comscore-4-out-of-5-smartphone-owners-use-device-to-shop-amazon-most-popular-mobile-retailer/|work=TechCrunch|publisher=AOL Inc|accessdate=27 June 2013|author=Leena Rao|date=19 September 2012}}</ref> Another study conducted in June 2013 concluded that 56% of American adults now owned a smartphone of some kind. Android and iPhone owners account for half of the cell phone user population. Higher income adults and those under age 35 lead the way when it comes to smartphone ownership.<ref>http://boletines.prisadigital.com/PIP_Smartphone_adoption_2013.pdf</ref>

Worldwide shipments of smartphones topped 1 billion units in 2013 (up 38% from 2012's 725 million) while comprising a 55% share of the mobile phone market in 2013 (up from 42% in 2012).<ref>{{cite web
| title = Worldwide Smartphone Shipments Top One Billion Units for the First Time, According to IDC
| author =	
| publisher = IDC
| date = January 2014	
| url = http://www.idc.com/getdoc.jsp?containerId=prUS24645514	
| accessdate = 2014-01-27	
}}</ref>

===By manufacturer===
[[File:Smartphones.jpg|thumb|[[Samsung]] smartphones with [[Android (operating system)|Android]] OS]]
In 2013, Samsung had 31.3 percent shipment [[market share]], a slight increase from 30.3 percent in 2012, while Apple was at 15.3 percent, a decrease from 18.7 percent in 2012. [[Huawei]], [[LG]] and [[Lenovo]] were at about 5 percent each, significantly better than 2012 figures, while others had about 40 percent, the same as the previous years figure. Only Apple lost market share, although their shipment volume still increased by 12.9 percent; the rest had significant increases in shipment volumes of 36 to 92 percent.<ref>{{cite web |url=http://www.engadget.com/2014/01/28/smartphone-sales-may-have-topped-1-billion-in-2013/ |title=Smartphone sales may have topped 1 billion in 2013, depending on who you ask |work=[[Engadget]] |author=Jon Fingas |date=January 28, 2014}}</ref> In Q1 of 2014, [[Samsung]] had a 31% share and Apple had 16%.<ref>{{cite web |url= http://www.techinasia.com/xiaomi-global-top-10-smartphone-shipments-q1-2014/|title= Xiaomi breaks into global top 10 for smartphone shipments, kicks out HTC|author= Steven Millward|date= May 13, 2014|accessdate= September 9, 2014|work= Tech In Asia}}</ref>

===By operating system===
{{main|Mobile operating system}}
The market has been dominated by the Android operating system since 2010. Android's market share (measured by units shipment) rose from 33.2% in Q4 2011 to 78.1% of the market in Q4 2013. Apple managed to oscillate their market share between 15% to 20.9% during the same period. BlackBerry's market share fell from 14.3% in Q4 2011 to 0.6% in Q4 2013. MS Windows Mobile market share rose from 1.5% to 3% during the same time frame.<ref name="2014 market share">{{cite web |url=http://www.idc.com/prodserv/smartphone-os-market-share.jsp |title=IDC: Smartphone OS Market Share |accessdate=March 26, 2014}}</ref>

As of the end of Q2 2014, Android was the most popular operating system, with a 84.7% market share, followed by iOS with 11.7%, Windows Phone with  2.5% and BlackBerry with 0.5%.<ref>{{cite web |url=http://www.idc.com/prodserv/smartphone-os-market-share.jsp |title=Smartphone OS Market Share, Q2 2014 |accessdate=September 27, 2014}}</ref>

====Historical sales figures (in millions of units)====

{| class="wikitable sortable" style="font-size: 85%; text-align: center; width: auto;"
|-
! Year
! Android (Google)
! iOS (Apple)
! Windows Mobile/Phone (Microsoft)
! BlackBerry (former RIM)
! Symbian (Nokia)
! Palm/WebOS (Palm/HP)
! Bada (Samsung)
! Other
|-
! 2007<ref name="gartner.com">[http://www.gartner.com/it/page.jsp?id=910112 Gartner Says Worldwide Smartphone Sales Reached Its Lowest Growth Rate With 3.7 Per Cent Increase in Fourth Quarter of 2008]. Gartner.com. Retrieved on 2012-08-09.</ref>
!
! 3.3
! 14.7
! 11.77
! 77.68
! 1.76
! 
! 
|-
! 2008<ref name="gartner.com"/>
!
! 11.42
! 16.5
! 23.15
! 72.93
! 2.51
!
!
|-
! 2009<ref>[http://www.gartner.com/it/page.jsp?id=1306513 Gartner Says Worldwide Mobile Phone Sales to End Users Grew 8 Per Cent in Fourth Quarter 2009; Market Remained Flat in 2009]. Gartner.com. Retrieved on 2012-08-09.</ref>
! 6.8
! 24.89
! 15.03
! 34.35
! 80.88
! 1.19
! 
!
|-
! 2010<ref>[http://www.gartner.com/it/page.jsp?id=1543014 Gartner Says Worldwide Mobile Device Sales to End Users Reached 1.6 Billion Units in 2010; Smartphone Sales Grew 72 Percent in 2010]. Gartner.com. Retrieved on 2012-08-09.</ref>
! 67.22
! 46.6
! 12.38
! 47.45
! 111.58
! 
! 
!
|-
! 2011<ref>{{cite web|title=Quarterly Device Sales In 2011|url=http://www.mobilestatistics.com/mobile-statistics|work=Mobile Statistics|publisher=Mobile Statistics|accessdate=25 July 2013|format=Infographic|year=2013}}</ref> 
! 219.52
! 89.26
! 8.77
! 51.54
! 93.41
! 
! 9.6
! 14.24
|-
! 2012<ref name="gartner2013">[http://www.gartner.com/newsroom/id/2665715 Gartner Says Annual Smartphone Sales Surpassed Sales of Feature Phones for the First Time in 2013]. Gartner.com. Retrieved on 2014-07-24.</ref>
! 451.62
! 130.13
! 16.94
! 34.21
!
!
! 15.9
! 47.20
|-
!2013<ref name="gartner2013"/>
!758.72
!150.79
!30.84
!18.61
!
!
!
!8.82
|}

==Issues==

===Battery life===
[[File:USB battery charger.jpg|thumbnail|A high-capacity portable battery charger]]
Compared to current generation non-smartphones, smartphone's battery life has generally been poor which has become a significant drain on customer satisfaction.<ref>{{cite web|title=J.D. Power and Associates Reports: Smartphone Battery Life has Become a Significant Drain on Customer Satisfaction and Loyalty|url=http://www.prnewswire.com/news-releases/jd-power-and-associates-reports-smartphone-battery-life-has-become-a-significant-drain-on-customer-satisfaction-and-loyalty-142765065.html|accessdate=11 September 2014}}</ref><ref>[http://www.zdnet.com/the-secret-behind-poor-smartphone-battery-life-7000032270/ ZDNet - The secret behind poor smartphone battery life]</ref><ref>[http://techland.time.com/2013/04/01/peak-battery-why-smartphone-battery-life-still-stinks-and-will-for-years/ Time - Peak Battery: Why Smartphone Battery Life Still Stinks, and Will for Years]</ref>

===Environmental===

Obtaining the resources required to create smartphones involves the mining of [[minerals]] such as [[coltan]], which are toxic to humans and wildlife.<ref name=":1">Ebersole, R 2003, 'Recycle Cell Phones, Reduce Toxic Trash', ''National Wildlife (World Edition)'', 41, 4, p. 14, Science Reference Center, EBSCOhost, retrieved 14 August 2013.</ref> Other raw materials, such as oils, copper, plastics, and solvents, have the potential to contaminate both the soil and groundwater.<ref name=":1"/> Smartphones also contain toxic chemicals such as lead, [[bromine]], [[chlorine]], [[Mercury (element)|mercury]], and [[cadmium]].<ref>'Mobile phones a pollution risk'2007, New Scientist, 194, 2600, p. 23, Science Reference Center, EBSCOhost, retrieved 14 August 2013.</ref>

The improper recycling of used smartphones damages the environment.<ref>"Cellphones: a pollution risk environment" 2007, Science news and science jobs from New Scientist. http://www.newscientist.com/article/mg19426006.500-cellphones-a-pollution-risk.html. Retrieved on 14 August 2013.</ref> Mobile phones can contain dangerous chemicals such as [[antimony]], cadmium, [[copper]], lead, [[arsenic]], [[nickel]] and [[zinc]],<ref name=":1"/> which can run off into surrounding water bodies or seep into soil contaminating wildlife and drinking water.<ref>Wall, Tim. (October 5, 2012) "Cellphones toxic to humans and Earth". http://news.discovery.com/earth/cell-phones-toxic-121005.html. Retrieved 14 August 2013.</ref>

===Worker conditions===

The [[capacitors]] in electronics use minerals mined in [[developing countries]]. Mines in [[Rwanda]], for example, have been associated with [[human rights]] and [[labor rights]] violations.<ref name=":0">“Coltan: a new blood mineral”. (2010, December 10). CBC.ca– Technology and Science. [http://www.cbc.ca/news/technology/story/2010/12/10/coltan-faq.html http://www.cbc.ca/new] s [http://www.cbc.ca/news/technology/story/2010/12/10/coltan-faq.html /technology/story/2010/12/10/coltan-faq.html]. Retrieved 14 August 2013.</ref> Workers, including children, have been forced to work at gunpoint while mining for smartphone materials.<ref name=":0" />

The electronics soldering in smartphones require tin, 30% of which comes from the Indonesian islands of [[Bangka Island|Bangka]] and [[Belitung]]. The tin extraction process has been identified as environmentally destructive and, as of September 2013, children are employed in hazardous conditions to extract tin.<ref>{{cite web|title=Mobile industry tackles tin problems after Friends of the Earth campaign|url=http://foe.co.uk/resource/press_releases/mobile_industry_bangka_31072013.html|work=Friends of the Earth|publisher=Friends of the Earth Trust/Limited|accessdate=24 September 2013|format=Press release|date=31 July 2013}}</ref>

===Social===
{{Main|Smartphone addiction}}
A University of Southern California study found that the [[Safe sex|unprotected]] [[adolescent sexuality|adolescent sexual]] activity was more common amongst owners of smartphones.<ref>[http://www.theregister.co.uk/2012/11/01/smartphones_more_sexually_active/ "SMARTPHONES make TEENS have SEX with STRANGERS."]</ref> A study conducted by the [[Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute]]'s (RPI) Lighting Research Center (LRC) concluded that smartphones, or any backlit devices, can seriously affect sleep cycles.<ref name=Colaner>{{cite news|last=Colaner|first=Seth|title=our Tablet and Smartphone Could Be Ruining Your Sleep|url=http://hothardware.com/News/Your-Tablet-and-Smartphone-are-Ruining-Your-Sleep-/|accessdate=22 January 2014|date=27 August 2012}}</ref>

===Legal===
{{Main|Smartphone wars}}
A "patent war" between Samsung and Apple started when the latter claimed that the original [[Samsung Galaxy S|Galaxy S]] Android phone copied the interface—and possibly the hardware—of Apple's iOS for the [[iPhone 3GS]].

{{Main|Mobile medical apps}}
With the raise in number of [[mobile medical apps]] in the market place, government regulatory agencies raised concerns on the safety of the use of such applications. These concerns were transformed into regulation initiatives world wide with the aim of safeguarding users from untrusted medical advice.<ref>Yetisen, A. K., Martinez-Hurtado, J. L., et al (2014). The regulation of mobile medical applications. Lab on a Chip, 14(5), 833-840. dx.doi.org/10.1039/C3LC51235E</ref>

===Security===

{{Main|Mobile security|Malware|Mobile virus|Media Transfer Protocol}}

Smartphone malware is more easily distributed through application stores that have minimal or no security mechanisms.<ref name="Juniper-malware">[http://globalthreatcenter.com/?p=2492 Mobile Malware Development Continues To Rise, Android Leads The Way].</ref><ref name=trustbus11>{{cite book|title=8th International Conference on Trust, Privacy & Security in Digital Business (TRUSTBUS-2011)|year=2011|publisher=Springer Berlin / Heidelberg|pages=49–61|author=Mylonas Alexios|authorlink=A Secure Smartphone Applications Roll-out Scheme|author2=Tsoumas Bill |author3=Dritsas Stelios |author4=Gritzalis Dimitris }}</ref>  Often malware is hidden in [[Copyright infringement of software|pirated]] versions of legitimate apps, which are then distributed through 3rd party app stores.<ref>{{cite news |url=http://www.androidpolice.com/2011/03/01/the-mother-of-all-android-malware-has-arrived-stolen-apps-released-to-the-market-that-root-your-phone-steal-your-data-and-open-backdoor/ |title = The Mother Of All Android Malware Has Arrived |work=Android Police |first=Android Police |date=March 6, 2011 }}</ref><ref>{{cite web |last=Perez |first=Sarah |url=http://www.readwriteweb.com/archives/android_vulnerability_so_dangerous_shouldnt_use_web_browser.php |title=Android Vulnerability So Dangerous, Owners Warned Not to Use Phone's Web Browser |publisher=Readwriteweb.com |date=2009-02-12 |accessdate=2011-08-08}}</ref> Malware risk also comes from what's known as an "update attack", where a legitimate application is later changed to include a malware component, which users then install when they are notified that the app has been updated.<ref name="Lookout-malware">{{cite web|url=http://www.appleinsider.com/articles/11/08/03/lookout_retrevio_warn_of_growing_android_malware_epidemic_note_apples_ios_is_far_safer.html |title=Lookout, Retrevo warn of growing Android malware epidemic, note Apple's iOS is far safer |publisher=Appleinsider.com |date=2011-08-03 |accessdate=2012-01-05}}</ref>

One out of three robberies involve the theft of a mobile phone. An online petition urging that smartphone makers to install [[kill switch]]es in their devices is underway.<ref>[http://www.sfexaminer.com/sanfrancisco/plea-urges-anti-theft-phone-tech/Content?oid=2447711 Aldax, Mike "Plea Urges Anti-Theft Phone Tech" ''San Francisco Examiner'' Friday, June 7, 2013 Page 5:]</ref>

In order to minimize the chances of being a victim of theft of mobile devices, there have been several apps created to help those out that may be in a dangerous situation. There are now apps that may aid in personal security by providing immediate assistance.

===Disturbing sleep===
Using smartphones late at night can disturb sleep due to the bright screen light affecting melatonin levels and sleep cycles.<ref>{{cite web|author=Luisa Dillner |url=http://www.theguardian.com/lifeandstyle/2013/jun/09/smartphones-tablets-in-bedroom-sleep |title=Should I keep my smartphone and tablet out of my bedroom? &#124; Life and style |publisher=The Guardian |accessdate=2014-06-17}}</ref><ref>{{cite web|url=http://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2013/06/130603163610.htm |title=Are smartphones disrupting your sleep? |publisher=ScienceDaily |accessdate=2014-06-17}}</ref><ref>{{cite web|author=Mahesh Sharma |url=http://www.smh.com.au/digital-life/digital-life-news/switching-off-your-smartphone-at-night-makes-you-more-productive-20140403-zqpc4.html |title=Switching off your smartphone at night makes you more productive |publisher=Smh.com.au |accessdate=2014-06-17}}</ref><ref>One of the best biological cues we have to [tell] what time of day it is, is light. And it turns out that blue light in particular is very effective at basically predicting when morning is,” Brian Zoltowski from the American Chemical Society [http://www.thehindu.com/todays-paper/tp-national/smart-phones-can-ruin-your-sleep/article6031259.ece]</ref>

==Other terms==

"[[Phablet]]", a [[portmanteau]] of the words ''phone'' and ''tablet'', describes smartphones with larger screens.<ref name="forbes">{{Citation | date = 2012-02-07 | url = http://www.forbes.com/sites/rogerkay/2012/02/07/is-the-market-ready-for-a-phablet/ | title = Is the Market Ready for a Phablet? | newspaper = Forbes |date=7 February 2012 |accessdate=2012-08-15}}</ref><ref name="pcmag">{{Citation 
| url = http://www.pcmag.com/slideshow/story/294004/enter-the-phablet-a-history-of-phone-tablet-hybrids 
| title = Enter the Phablet: A History of Phone-Tablet Hybrids 
| publisher = pcmag.com, Sasha Segan, February 13, 2012}}</ref>

"Superphone" is also used by some companies to market phones with unusually large screens and other expensive features.<ref>[http://mashable.com/2010/07/12/superphone/ What Makes a Smartphone a Superphone?] Mashable.com</ref><ref>[http://www.techradar.com/news/phone-and-communications/mobile-phones/superphone-vs-smartphone-what-s-the-difference--1055564 Superphone vs smartphone: what's the difference?] Techradar.com</ref>

==See also==
{{Portal|Internet}}
* [[BlackBerry thumb]]
* [[Camera phone]] and [[videophone]]
* [[Comparison of smartphones]]
* [[Dumbphone]]
* [[List of digital distribution platforms for mobile devices]]
* [[Media Transfer Protocol]]
* [[Mobile broadband]] connectivity
* [[Mobile Internet device]] (MID) and [[personal digital assistant]] (PDA)
* [[Mobile operating system]]
* [[Mobile phone]]
* [[Second screen]]
* [[Screen protector]]

==References==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

== External links ==
* {{Commons category-inline|Smartphones}}

{{Cloud computing}}
{{Mobile phones}}
{{Table Mobile operating systems}}
{{Computer sizes}}
{{Telecommunications}}

[[Category:Smartphones|Smartphones]]
[[Category:Mobile phones]]
[[Category:Cloud clients]]
[[Category:Information appliances]]
	  </text>
      <sha1>b6uz5wwkljnmhrnptmtrs4tzb9wji8b</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>

     <page>
    <title>Smartphones</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>18707</id>
    <revision>
      <id>5847450</id>
      <parentid>5843148</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-08-28T15:58:47Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>95.105.179.10</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment></comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">
		#REDIRECT [[Smartphone]]
	  </text>
      <sha1>b6uz5wwkljnmhrnptmtrs4tzb9wji8b</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>